music
music
applause
applause
So today we actually have two keynote speakers
那麼今天呢我們事實上有兩位主講人
but
但是呢
Ah, academician Zhang Shenghua, he is very polite
啊張生華院士他客氣
he
他
Ah, a self-proclaimed shadow speaker
啊自居為影言人
He will speak for 20 minutes
他等一下要講20分鐘
So
那麼
So the speaker is Li Guangdi
所以主講人是李光蒂
Teacher, the two of them performed together
老師啊他們兩位聯合演出
Joint performance
聯合演出
What about today's keynote speaker, Dr. Li Guangdi?
那麼今天的主講人李光蒂博士呢
Is a researcher at the Institute of History, Academia Sinica
是中研院歷史研究所的研究員
then arizona state university
那麼是美國亞利桑那州立大學
PhD in Archaeological Anthropology
考古人類學的博士
He's mostly doing ecological archaeology
他主要是做生態考古學
that is, through archaeological remains
也就是透過考古學的遺存
to estimate
來推估
recovery
復原
Then the food resources at that time
那麼當時的食物的資源
Ecological environment and climate
生態環境氣候
including the population
包括人口的數量
Including the time the site was occupied, etc.
包括這個遺址佔據的時間等等問題
So this is a highly integrated technology
那麼這是一個高度結合科技
imagination
想像力
one of archaeological work and more
考古工作等等的一個
Your knowledge is very important
很重要的你們學問
his main
他主要的
Except for the Academia Sinica
這個除了在中研院之外呢
He is also in the School of Anthropology of Tsing University
他也在清大人類學院
That is to say, the Earth Science Department of Normal University
就是說師大的這個地球科學系
and Tainan University of the Arts
以及台南藝術大學
first lesson
首課
Then his main scope of work
那他主要的工作範圍
is in
是在
Hengchun Peninsula
恆春半島
and Tainan Science Park
還有台南科學園區
I can testify that he is almost
我可以作證他在恆春半島已經幾乎就是
Ah, a representative of public opinion
啊民意代表級的人物啦
I remember twenty, thirty or twenty years ago
有記得二三二十幾年前
when i went there once
我有一次去那裡的時候
He knows almost everyone there
他幾乎認識那邊所有
everyone around
附近所有的人
so i know he's over there
所以我知道他在那邊
deep plowing
深耕密子
There is quite a deep
有相當深厚的這個
local strength
地方實力
Today's shadow speaker is Academician Zhang Zhenghua
今天的這個影言人是張政華院士
Well, he's also a research fellow at the History Institute of the Majestic Academy.
那麼他也是莊嚴院歷史研究所的特評研究員
He is a Ph.D. from Harvard University
他是美國哈佛大學的博士
His main research interest is Taiwan
他的主要研究興趣是台灣
Southeast Asia
東南亞
and this archaeological site in South China
以及這個華南地區的這個考古
Research
研究
He was in 2002 to 2006
他曾經在2002年到2006年
secondment single
借調單人
Director of National Taiwan Museum of Prehistory
國立台灣史前博物館的館長
Chang Hsien is of course the current archaeological leader in Taiwan
張憲當然是台灣現在的考古學的領導人
Three of the many jobs he now performs
他現在執行的很多工作中有三件
One is the archaeology of Nanke
一個是南科的考古
One is the archeology of Baxian Cave
一個是八仙洞的考古
that is a very important site
那是非常重要的遺址
One is to lead the underwater archeology team of Academia Sinica
一個就是領導中研院的水下考古團隊
He was elected as an academician of Academia Sinica on the Third World in 2014
他在2014年當選為中研院就第三世界院士
The topic the two of them are going to talk about today is Nanke Archeology
他們兩位今天要講的題目是南科考古
5000 years of discovery of Taiwan
發現台灣五千年
You may have noticed that Nanke Archeology has been going on for 20 years
各位或許注意到南科考古已經前後進行了20年
Voted one of the top ten archaeological sites in the world last year
在去年被選為世界十大考古遺址之一
Then I just noticed
那麼我剛才也才注意到
This is the first time that Nanke archeology has been included in the knowledge award test report
這個是南科考古第一次在知識獎驗報告
Their work I think this opportunity is very rare
他們的工作我覺得這個機會非常難得
Then this archaeological site
那麼這個考古遺址
Worked without knowledge for 20 years
知識不見的工作了20年
said
說的
touched area
觸及的面積
2000 hectares of independent
有2000公頃的獨立
A total of 70 archaeological sites were discovered
總計發現70處的考古遺址
Large-scale excavations were carried out at 34 of them
在其中34處進行大規模的挖掘
The total excavated area reached more than 120,000 average meters
挖掘的總面積達到12多萬平均公尺
More than 120,000 square meters
12萬多的平方公尺
The abundance of archaeological materials unearthed
所出土的考古材料之豐富
all kinds of colors
各式各樣形形色色
Because he used to be the director of this institute
因為以前是這個所的所長
So I also visited
所以我也去看過
very rich
非常的豐富
I'm afraid it's Asia, I dare not talk nonsense
恐怕是亞洲我不敢亂講
One of the largest archaeological sites
規模最大的考古遺址之一
Whether it is naughty, stone, jade, bone, etc.
不管是淘氣、石器、玉器、骨器等等
Taiwan's first dog
台灣的第一條狗
Taiwan's first
台灣的第一道子
all from this ruins
都是從這個遺址
There are more than 2,000 unearthed
光出土的就有一海就有2000多
More than 2000 dramas
超過2000劇以上
spanned over 5000 years
跨越的時間長達5000年
rare archaeological site
難得考古的遺址
As the climate of the South Island and foot of the world
作為世界南島與足的氣候
It is very important to migrate
跟遷移有非常重要的
It is very important to understand this issue
了解這個問題有非常重要的作用
Well, this archaeological team is currently conducting
那麼這個考古隊目前已經進行
Arrangement and analysis of cultural relics unearthed in one place in twenty one places
二十一處一處出土文物的整理跟分析
Sorting and analysis, wow, are two different things again.
整理跟分析 哇 又是兩回事了
Archeology sucks.
考古很廢事啊
And it's very hard, working with the soil all day long
而且很辛苦啊 整天跟土在那邊做
It's really hard work
做辦 真的很辛苦
After that, it needs to be analyzed and sorted out.
然後完了還要分析 還要整理
Still need to organize and analyze
還要整理 還要分析
Also do DNA testing
還要做DNA檢測
Gotta do all kinds of this wow amazing amazing
還要做各式各樣的這個 哇 不得了 不得了
Then this site enriches the new era of Taiwan
那麼這個遺址充實了台灣新時期時代
Understanding of Early Human Lifestyles
早期人類生活方式的了解
Also provides more information about the ancient Austronesian peoples
也提供更多有關古代南島民族
New Evidence and Understanding of Ocean-to-Ocean Diffusion from the Asian Continent
由亞洲大陸向海洋擴散的新證據跟新理解
Of course, this site is because of the huge size of Thailand
當然這個遺址因為泰國龐大
I can't introduce them all here
我沒辦法在這裡一一介紹
Should we just welcome Academician Zhang Zhenghua to do camp performances first?
我們現在是不是就歡迎張正華院士先做營演
Thanks
謝謝
Thank you, Dean Wang, for letting me come here to give an introduction.
謝謝王院長讓我來這邊給個引言
Thank you very much too
也非常謝謝大家
be honest
老實來擺盲之中
Come and listen to our Nanke archaeological report
來聽我們的這個南科考古的報告
I think today this archaeological
我想今天本來這個考古
This knowledge feast of the past
過去的這個知識饗宴
I've said it twice
我已經講過兩次了
So this time I would like to invite our colleagues
所以這一次我本來想請我們的同仁
Mr. Li Huangqing will talk about it
這個李黃慶先生他就來講
Later, our dean helped me to return the ticket.
後來我們院長幫我打回票了
Say no, the two of you
說不行你們兩個來講
So finally we assign
所以最後我們分配一下
I said I'll be the intro
我說我來做引言
Or ask our colleagues to do this
還是請我們的同仁來做這個
a major report
一個主要的報告
So what I'm going to talk about today is
那我今天的這個主要講的
I just want to make this Nanke archaeological
就是想要把這個南科考古的一個
ins and outs
來龍去脈
can give a little introduction
可以稍微做一點介紹
Everyone can have an impression
大家可以有一個印象
Then the following enters our topic
然後下面才進入到我們主題
How Nanke Archeology Discovered Taiwan for 5,000 Years
就是南科考古如何發現台灣五千年
And how to discover the five thousand years of Taiwan
以及怎麼去發現台灣五千年
this is the topic of today's speech
這是今天演講的主題
then this
那麼這個
I think the reason why
我想這件事之所以
The vice president will take a fancy to us
這個副院長會看中我們
let us come
讓我們來
come here to sing the play
來這邊參唱這齣戲
Basically these two brands
基本上就是這兩個牌子
Because in December last year we participated in a
因為在去年12月我們參加一個
This is an archeology of a world
這是一個世界的一個考古
this is in shanghai
這是在上海
One held in Shanghai in 2015
2015年在上海辦的一個
The World Archaeological Forum
這個世界考古論壇
Then we propose this project
那我們這一個project就提出來
A Description of Our One Contents
一個我們的一個內容的說明
then by this
然後被這個
Selected as the so-called top ten archaeological discoveries in the world
選為這個所謂世界十大考古發現
The first is field archaeological discoveries
第一就是田野考古發現
so we get two medals
所以我們就得到兩個獎牌
I was a little disappointed when I got it
後來拿了以後就有點失望
looks heavy
看起來蠻重的
Later, I found out that it was probably signed inside.
後來發現原來是裡面大概是籤的
Du layer of gold on the outside
外面是杜一層金
If two gold medals
如果是兩塊金牌的話
That's pretty worth it
那就就相當值錢了
but it will
不過這一定會
This is what we do for the Central Court
這也是我們替中央院
You can also fight for a little glory
也可以爭取一點榮耀
because this is about
因為這個講的是
There are 40 top scholars and experts in the world
有世界上40位的頂尖級的學者專家
jointly reviewed
共同來審查的
and then to grant
然後來授予的
So we also feel honored
所以我們也覺得很榮幸
to get such an award
能夠得到這樣一個獎
then this is
那麼這個是
So today I probably want to basically explain the ins and outs of this plan.
所以我今天大概想基本上把這一個計畫的一個來龍去脈
First of all, let me give you a report
首先來給各位來做一個報告
I think our basic archeology is the study of history
我想我們這個基本上面考古學它是研究歷史
What about our special Taiwan archeology in Taiwan
那麼我們在台灣的特別台灣考古呢
Basically, it is necessary to study and study the history of Taiwan.
基本上面是要去研究也是要研究台灣的歷史
But what about Taiwan's history?
但是台灣的歷史呢它的這個
written history is very short
有文字的歷史非常短
Everyone knows about 300 to 400 years
大家也知道大概300年400年
very short
非常短
So we all know this
所以這個在我們大家都知道
In fact, what is the history of our people in Taiwan?
事實上我們台灣的人歷史呢
It's definitely not 300 or 400 years now
其實現在絕不是300年或400年
Now at least according to our current archaeological data
那現在至少根據我們目前的考古資料
Just now the vice president of the academy mentioned that I am personally in Baixuandong
剛剛院副院長提到我個人在白軒洞
This research has been done for several years
最近做了好幾年的這個研究
So now it's almost certain
那麼現在幾乎可以肯定呢
The history of human habitation in Taiwan is now 30,000 years
台灣人類居住的歷史現在30,000年
At least 30,000 years at the latest
至少最晚最晚就30,000年
those 30,000 years
那30,000年
Then let's make a comparison of Taiwan's history
那我們把台灣的歷史要做一個比較的話
Then he only accounts for the written history of Taiwan?
那他只佔台灣有文字的歷史呢
Only 1.3% of Taiwan's human history
只占台湾人类历史的1.3%而已
So a little bit of the rest of the time is without text
所以一点点其他时间都是没有文字的
don't know
都不知道的
unknown in the past
过去不知道的
Later, archaeological data showed him
后来经过考古资料把他显示出来的
If viewed on a mid-plane
如果放在一个中面上来看的话
Written History Accounts for Taiwan History
有文字的历史占台湾历史
only 48 seconds
只占48秒而已
Other such a big circle
其他这么一大圈
basically no text
基本上都是没有文字的
so what if there is no text
所以没有文字怎么办呢
must rely on archeology
必须要靠考古学
So the vice president of archeology just mentioned
所以考古刚刚副院长提到
archeology is hard
考古学很辛苦
to go to the fields to do cutting and digging
要到田野去做伐掘
Come back to organize, analyze, research
回来要整理 要分析 要研究
The purpose is to reconstruct the history of Taiwan
目的就是要重建台湾的历史
Especially 99.0% of Taiwan
特别是台湾99.几%
This history needs to be borrowed from archeology
这个历史都需要借着由考古学
information searched evidence searched
搜寻的资料 搜寻的证据
Then come and help us rebuild
然后来帮我们去做重建
In addition, archaeological data
另外就是考古学资料
Most of them are sold underground
大部分都是在卖在地底下
say to dig, to dig
说要去挖 要去发掘
do fieldwork
做田野调查
also in the water
同时也在水里面
submerged in water
被淹没在水里面
So we inside the Taiwan Strait
所以我们台湾海峡里面
there are many flooded
有很多被淹没的
or silent these ancients
或沉默的这些古代人
transplant or transplant
移植或者移基或者移物
Well, this aspect actually needs to rely on Gu Xue's research.
那这方面呢其实都需要靠谷学的研究
So the vice president mentioned it just now. I personally also presided over an underwater valley team of our hospital recently.
所以刚刚副院长提下呢我个人最近也主持一个本院的水下靠谷队
So the purpose is around Taiwan
那么目的呢就在台湾周边
Especially the Taiwan Strait or the South China Sea
特别是台湾海峡啊或者南海
To do this underwater survey of these valleys
要做这个水下的这些靠谷的调查
Well, this is so relying on the Gu family to go to the field to find information
那么这个所以靠谷家竟然要到田野去找资料
So a lot of envy depends on the Gu family
所以这个很多羡慕靠谷家啊
often travel outside
经常在外面游山玩水
Take a tour of the mountains and rivers, what about me personally?
游山玩水一下我个人呢
I don't know how to climb a mountain above the sea
不晓得到海上面去一下爬山啊
It's all good, in fact, he doesn't know all kinds of hard work.
都很好其实他不知道各种辛苦啊
You only know if you have a bag
这有把包才知道啊
In addition, going to the sea is the same as going to Mizuno to investigate.
那么另外到海里也是一样在水野去要去调查
So, therefore, whether these things are in the water
那么所以因此呢这些东西无论是在水里面
Or a space on land that can store these valley-based data?
或在陆地上面能够保存这些靠谷资料的这一个space呢
basically become a size
基本上面成为一个size
It's just a transplant
就是一个移植啊
And what about these transplants, of course
那么这些移植呢当然
We must rely on the research and analysis of Gu Xue
要必须要去靠谷学的研究分析
What about after analyzing this research?
那透过这个研究分析之后呢
Only then can we make the incompleteness of human history
我們才能夠把人類歷史的殘缺
complement it
把它補充起來
So Taiwan is facing 99.9% of Taiwan's history
所以臺向台灣99.9%的這一個歷史
archaeological data
都需要藉由考古學的資料
the study of archaeology
考古學的研究
to supplement
來加以補充
to enrich
來加以充實
So therefore the archaeological site
所以因此考古遺址
It is a very important asset of a culture
它是一個非常重要的一個文化的資產
if you say don't pay attention to it
你如果說是不去注意它
that would easily destroy it
那很容易就把它毀壞掉了
so like this
所以像這樣子
Our current construction in various aspects in Taiwan
我們台灣現在目前的各方面的建設
In fact, the ruins are constantly being destroyed.
其實不斷地在破壞遺址
very many ruins
非常多的遺址
This is a No. 13 ruins that I rescued in the past
這個是在過去我搶救的一個十三號遺址
almost gone now
現在幾乎也沒有了
most are gone
大部分都沒有了
Like many ruins in Taiwan
像台灣很多很多的遺址
Just like that, it was dug up by strange hands.
就這樣子被怪手就挖掉了
once dug out
一旦挖掉了
You can't rely on this anymore
你不可能再靠這個了
Let's recreate our past human history
來再重建我們過去人類的歷史
Of course now slowly
當然現在慢慢的
our government
我們政府
our people
我們的民眾
also slowly understand
也慢慢的了解到
These ruins should be protected
應該去保護這些的遺址
Now there are many means of protection
那現在有很多的保護的手段
The first is through the law
那第一個是透過法律
Now currently we have a
現在目前我們有一個叫
Cultural Assets Preservation Act
文化資產保存法
This law will require all engineering construction
這個法就會要求所有的工程建設
in the development process
在開發過程裡面
or development must be done before
或開發之前都一定要去做
Always investigate and evaluate
一直調查評估
Then if it damages the chair
然後假如會對椅子造成損壞
so you have to go and that's it
所以你必須要去就這些
This project of yours needs to be adjusted
你的這個工程要進行調整
or how to protect these chairs
或者怎麼樣去保護這些椅子
The other is the Environmental Impact Assessment Act
另外一個就是環境影響評估法
This law also clearly stipulates
這個法也明白的規定
all because of development
所有因為開發行為
adverse impact on the environment
對環境所產生不良影響的
environmental impact assessment
就應該要實施環境影響評估
This assessment also includes cultural and educational
這個評估裡面也包含了文教
or cultural facilities
或文化的這些設施
or chair of culture
或文化的椅子
In this way, if the development
這樣子的話假如開發
we can avoid
我們才能夠避免
Destroy these chairs for development
因為開發而破壞掉這些椅子
So therefore this archaeologist recently
所以因此這個考古學家最近
We especially know Taiwan's
我們特別知道台灣的
In fact, there are not many people
其實人數不多
We are a very small group
我們是非常少的一個族群
But we've taken on a pretty big job
但是我們卻承擔了相當大的任務
Various developments in Taiwan now
現在台灣的各種各樣的開發
In fact, a lot of things have to be done
其實很多都必須要去做
do archaeological research
做考古學的調查
Do an archaeological assessment
做考古學的評估
like this one
像這一個
So many people joked that we said
所以很多人笑話我們說
Archaeologists in Taiwan are the fire brigade
台灣的考古學家就是救火隊
Why did the firefighters accuse the police of going to the fire?
救火隊員為什麼要指案去救火
Firefighting is not firefighting
救火不是救火
is to rescue or protect these ruins
就是搶救或者去保護這些遺址
then in general
那麼一般而言
There are several ways to protect the site of this archaeological team
這個考古學隊遺址的保護有幾種辦法
The first one is that I just ask it to stop development
第一個是我就要求它停止開發
If the road or railway is going to pass by
這個假如公路或者鐵路要經過的時候
sorry
對不起
this site is very important
這個遺址非常重要
very valuable
非常有價值
then you have to change your course
那麼你必須要去改變你的路線
Change the way you build
改變你的施工方式
The second is to change the development content
第二個是變更開發內容
That is to say, if this highway
就是說假如這一條高速公路
to pass through this site
要通過這個遺址
And this site is a very valuable site
而這個遺址就是非常有價值的遺址
after you remove it
你去掉它之後
will have an impact on our entire history
會對我們整個歷史會產生影響
I'm sorry
那對不起
then you're going to change your
那麼你要去改變你的
But the project cannot be changed
但是工程又不能夠變更
Building highways like Taiwan is difficult
像台灣的建築高速公路很困難
It's actually very difficult for you to make it change course
你要讓它改變路線其實非常困難的
not only about economics
不只涉及到經濟
issues related to politics
涉及到政治的問題
So this time I will ask
所以這個時候我會要求
You change the development content
你變更開發內容
just change a way
就是變更一個方式
If this company can use high-priced bridge currency
假如這個公司可以用高價橋通貨
Do not destroy this site
而不許破壞這個遺址
these can look like this
這些可以這樣子
or one place one factory
或者一個地方一個工廠
I let you change its position
我讓你變更它的位置
keep it here
這邊保留起來
as a green space
作為一個綠地
or for the park
或者為公園
Then the third is finally no way
然後第三個是最後是沒有辦法了
Going to rescue and excavate
就要去進行搶救發掘
Connotation of unearthed sites
要對出土遺址的內涵
to record
加以記錄
to be unearthed
加以出土
this is a last resort
這是最後的一個辦法
Well like we are in Tainan Science Park
那麼像我們在台南科學園區
Today it is mainly called Nanke Archeology
今天主要叫南科考古
Mainly refers to Tainan Science Park
主要指台南科學園區
Then this Tainan Branch
那麼這個台南科
we go
我們過去
The Nanke archaeological team of our aid institute
我們這個座援院的南科考古隊
we are in the joint camp
我們在聯合營
15 years of field work
做了15年的田野工作
Every year is the soil of Seoul
每一年的都是漢城土
struggle there
在那邊奮鬥
then this part
那麼這個部分
This is our picture
我們這個就是這個圖的
It's from Nanke
就是南科的
Currently we are in Nanke
目前我們在南科
a large number of ruins were found
就發現了大量的遺址
In fact, the source of this work
其實這個工作的來源
It's actually a very coincidental
其實是一個非常的偶然
this accident
這個偶然
Because this was in the 81st year of the Republic of China
因為這是在民國81年的時候
Executive Yuan
行政院
It is to balance domestic
它就是為了要均衡國內的
technological development
科技發展
So it was decided to build a second science park in Tainan
所以決定在台南建立第二個科學園區
The first one is Hsinchu Science Park
第一個是新竹科學園區
the second is in the south
第二個是在南部
Then choose its position at this time
那麼這個時候要選定它的位置
Finally, the county in Tainan was selected.
最後就選定了在台南的縣
Tainan County
當時台南縣
This Shanhua New City
這個善化 新市
And this place in the middle of the three townships of Anding
還有安定這三個鄉中間的這個地方
This place was originally a farm in Taitang.
這個地方原來是一個台塘的乾測的一個農場
We know that many developments in Taiwan
我們知道台灣很多開發
In the end, the land was found in Taitang
最後遭土地都是找台塘
Taitang is a big landlord
台塘是大地主
So here is a big farm of Zhenong in Taitang
所以這邊是一個很大的這個台塘的浙農的農場
So I chose this side as this
所以後來把這邊選為這個
A base for Taiwan's second science park
台灣的第二個科學園區的一個基地
what about this time
那這個時候呢
Of course it will cause a lot of problems
當然就會引起很多問題
There are many places to grab this position
很多地方都要搶這個位置
So like the Lu tribe in Kaohsiung at that time
所以像當時在高雄的陸族
they want
他們也要
Why Tainan and not Kaohsiung
為什麼在台南不在高雄
so we have to make noise
所以就也要吵
The whole society has been making noise
整個社會上一直在鬧
and after
後來呢
The unit that disrupted the chaos at that time was the National Science Council
這個當時的阻亂單位是國科會
The National Science Council will find me
國科會呢就找我
I wonder if there are any ruins here?
就問是不是這邊真有遺址呢
He said that he said that there are many ruins in the Lu nationality.
他說他就陸族說裡面很多遺址
You can't develop, you will soon destroy the ruins
你不能開發,你快會破壞遺址
Later I accepted his commission
後來我就接受了他委託
In 1984, a half-year investigation was conducted
在民國84年就做了一個半年的調查
After investigation, it was found that
後來調查之後,果然發現了
Indeed there are ruins
的確是有遺址
So I gave the National Science Conference at that time
所以我就給了當時的國科會議
At that time, the chairman of the committee was Guo Nanhong
那時候主任委員是郭南鴻
Chairman Guo
郭主任委員
i gave the report
我給了報告
I said that there are not only ruins here
我說這邊不但有遺址
And it's full of stars
而且是滿天星斗
why?
為什麼呢?
because of this place
因為這個地方
To the north is Zeng Wenxi, and over there is the Saltwater Creek
北邊是曾文西,那邊是鹽水溪
These two rivers are the most prone to flooding
這兩條河流是最容易泛爛的河流
So this trouble in the past
所以過去這個煩瀾
If there is no driver to bother you, a lot of dirt will accumulate
沒司機煩瀾就會堆積了很多的土
so few leftovers from the past
那麼寡過去人類的遺流
buried under the ground
整個埋在地底下了
So the ground here
所以這邊地下面
We reckon it's full of stars
我們估計是滿天星斗
dense like stars
像星星一樣密布的
very relics
非常有遺址
I said you will have problems in the future
我說你將來一定會碰到問題
development will encounter problems
開發一定會碰到問題
what about the end
那最後呢
But the whole project has already started
就但是這工程整個都已經開工了
all booked
都訂了
So in the end we got approval from the competent authority
所以最後我們經過主管機關同意之後
We've done a lot of
我們很多大部分都進行了
salvage excavation
搶救的發掘
A small part is keeping it as an in situ reserve
小部分是把它做為一個現地的保留
Tainan Science Park
是台南科學園區
I think everyone knows its location
它的位置我想大家都知道
In Shanhua, in Xinshi, in Anding
在善化 在新市 在安定
Probably its area is more than 1000 hectares
大概它的面積有1000多公頃的一個面積
That side is 1043 hectares
那這邊是1043公頃
This was used as a view of Taitang at that time.
這個是當時 作為看這個台塘的
You are dry on this farm
這個農場 你都是種乾澀
was desolate
當時一片荒涼
that's totally different now
那現在完全不一樣了
Now it is a very modern science and technology park
現在就是非常現代化的科技園區
Therefore, starting from the 1985 of the Republic of China
所以在這個從民國85年開始
we start the rescue
我們開始進行搶救
Unexpectedly, it took more than ten years to rescue him once he was rescued.
沒想到一搶救就搶救了十幾年
Why
為什麼
Nanke continues to develop
南科不斷地開發
Then there are transplants
然後就不斷地出現移植
Then why? Because the sky is full of stars
那為什麼呢 因為滿天星斗
Stars in the sky basement transplant
天上星星 地下室移植
So we have been developing
所以我們就一直開發裡面
just keep discovering
就是不斷地發現
keep discovering and then have to deal with
不斷地發現 然後就必須要處理
After treatment, we must do rescue
處理以後 我們必須要做搶救
So we can see as
所以我們可以作為看
We have five stages of rescue
我們有五個階段的搶救
From the 1984 of the Republic of China is the first stage
從民國84年是第一階段
Then the second one is 85 years
然後第二個是85年
The third stage is 92 years
第三階段是92年
The fourth stage is 94 years
第四階段是94年
Now it's 94 to 99
現在是94年到99年
Then, five stages of rescue work were done.
那這個做了五個階段的這個搶救工作
Then what we salvage is a large-scale excavation
那這個我們搶救的就是大規模的發掘
As a look at this, what we move one by one is the exploration pit we excavated.
作為看這個我們一個動一個動的就是我們發掘的探坑
As a look at our chairs, each chair is made on a large scale
作為看我們的這個每一個椅子都做大規模的
Excavate as many toys as possible from the ground
盡可能的把地下的玩物都能夠發掘出來
in a very systematic record
在一個很有系統的一個記錄
As a matter of fact, each excavation is such a large-scale excavation.
那作為看這個每一次的發掘都是這麼大規模的這種發掘
are very large
都是非常大規模的
Then we dig the rest at night
那我們剩下的在晚上發掘
Because sometimes when he is constructing
因為有時候他施工的時候呢
must be in a hurry
要必須趕時間
This is our factory building in Qimei’s Qimei
這個是我們在起美的起美的這個一個廠房
because he said they already took the order
因為他他說他們已經接受訂單了
If he does not start work for a day, the factory will not be completed and work will not start
他假如一天不開工工廠不建不成不開工
his loss is a terrible loss
他的損失就不得了的損失
So what about this matter?
那所以這個事情呢
And at the same time, the room is already under construction and all the machines are ready.
而且同時已經在建這個房機都打好了
So we have to do it within 45 days
所以我們必須要在45天之內呢
think about these chairs
想就完這些椅子
This is what a staff member does
這個就是做一個工作人員的
are local farmers
都是當地的農民
Then we became each very experienced archaeologists
後來我們變成每一個都變成很有經驗的考古學家
This one is that we and my staff were only four people
這一個是我們當初跟我的工作人員才四個人
Finally we got to a few years later
最後我們到了幾年之後
become such a large and huge team
變成這麼一個大的龐大的隊伍
That's what everyone does now
這就是做一個現在每一個人
Actually they really like working for us
其實他們非常喜歡給我們工作
why?
為什麼呢?
Originally they were farmers from nearby villages
本來他們是附近農村的農民
Later, their land was confiscated because of the Science Park.
後來因為科學園區把他們土地徵收掉了
They don't work anymore
他們反而沒有工作了
so we just happen to have jobs
所以剛好我們有工作
he has joined us
他有加入我們
Still interested in doing this
還有興趣的來做這個事情
It makes sense to do this
很有意義的來做這個事情
So we went through 15 years of field work
所以我們經過了15年的田野工作
We have about 50 vents in total
我們總共有大概發洩50幾處
Later, it gradually increased to more than 80 ruins
後來慢慢增加到80幾處的遺址
34 of them
那其中有34處
We have extensively excavated
我們經過大規模的發掘
So just now Fu Yuanyang mentioned
所以剛剛傅遠洋提到
We have released several million pieces of these cultural relics in the future
我們發了以後的幾百萬件的這些文物
we are not in the warehouse
我們不是放在倉庫裡面
still need one by one
還是要一件一件的
to be organized
要加以整理
Only then can this history be recreated
才能夠把這個歷史再重新
Rediscover it from these materials
从这些资料里面再把它重新的发掘出来
So this is a support that we have also become the Ministry of Science and Technology.
所以这个是一个我们目前也成为科技部的支持
We are currently continuing to nine years
我们目前也不断的到九年的时间
Continuously analyzing these cultural relics
不断的在进行这些文物的分析
Rescue us also works with some technology
抢救我们也和一些科技的合作
We are like the ones in the hospital, we are like the new cloud doctor, and the doctor is also present
我们像院里面的我们像新云医型博士也在场
We he both do analysis of the millet of these rice plants
我们他都做植物的这些稻米的小米的分析
There are also some medical analysis, etc.
还有一些医传学的分析等等
We still do these parts
这些部分我们目前都还做
But from inside
但是从一点一滴里面
We slowly put at least the 5,000-year history of Nanke in Taiwan
我们慢慢地把台湾至少南科的五千年的历史
can build it up
可以把它充建起来
At this time we are in Nanke as a watch
这个时候我们在南科作为看
All of these found in each of these ruins
所有发现的这些每一个都是这些遺址
Then there are some ruins that are salvaged on a large scale
然后有一些遺址就大规模的抢救
massive excavation
大规模的发掘
These guys have played a lot
这些人玩过非常多
Naughty, Stone, Jade, Bone, Iron, Bronze, etc.
淘气、石器、玉器、骨器、铁器、铜器等等
At the same time, we also found more than 2,000 wooden sticks
同时我们还发现有两千多座的木杖
It means that there are more than 2,000 human bones
就代表有两千多座的人骨
This human bone is based on osteology
这个人骨对靠骨学的
this is very very important
這件事非常非常重要
It not only provides an understanding of the human body in the past
它不只提供了解過去人類的身體
and disease
而且疾病
But the composition of the population etc.
但是人口的組成等等
can provide some very important information
都可以提供很重要的一些訊息
so now we are a
所以現在我們是一個
About the cultural relics found in Nanke
大概南科所發現的文物
can be summed up
可以歸納起來
Can help it have ten culture periods
可以幫它有十個文化期
The earliest is five thousand years
最早的是五千年
about four thousand eight
大概是四千八
up to five thousand
可以到五千
The latest one below can arrive
下面最晚的可以到
Han people in the early Ming and Qing Dynasties
早期的明清時代的漢人
So overall we differentiate into
所以整個我們區分成
Divided into ten cultural wonders
就分了十個文化的奇象
In every miracle
那這個每一個奇象裡面
have a very rich content of these
都有非常豐富的這些內容
Then inside each content
然後每一個內容裡面
can tell us
都可以告訴我們
a lot of history about the past
很多有關於過去的歷史
So this is what I want today below
所以這個是今天我想下面
Dr Li Fangji
李框季博士
for each culture period
他就會就每一個文化期
like found inside
像裡面的發現
and how do we analyze
以及我們怎麼樣去做分析
doing research?
做研究呢
to give you a report
來給各位來做一個報告
I'm having a hard time
我就很艱難的
give you an introduction
給各位介紹一個介紹
thank you all
謝謝大家
next one
下面一份
Thank you Vice President Wang
謝謝王副院長
He came to Nanke twice during his tenure
這個他在他的任內來我們南科兩次
So this is a big thank you for his support and encouragement.
所以這個是非常感謝他的支持跟鼓勵
So this can have today
所以這個能夠有今天呢
he contributed
他功不可沒
This is good
這個好
Then I will follow in the footsteps of Mr. Zhang
那接下來呢我就跟著張先生的這個腳步
This Nanke archaeological discovery in Taiwan for 5,000 years
這個南科考古發現台灣五千年
In fact I want to tell you
事實上我想要跟各位講
Just now Mr. Zhang told me to remove this one
剛剛本來張先生叫我把這一張拿掉
I said without your medal
我說沒有你那個獎牌呢
in fact one of each
事實上是各有一份
He has his medal and I have one of mine
他有他的獎牌我也有我的一個獎牌
But what about the one on the side and the one on the right?
可是呢旁邊的這一張右邊的這一張呢
only one
就只有一張吧
Seems
好像是
What about this one?
那這一張呢
This is what really explains the content of our award.
才是真正說明的那個我們得獎的這個內容
Well, of course, if it wasn't for this one
好,那當然如果不是有這一張的話
Of course, there seems to be no chance to stand here today.
當然今天也好像沒有機會站在這邊
This is indeed the case
這個確實是這樣
First of all, let me explain to you
首先呢還是跟各位說明一下
I should have no chance
我應該是沒有機會
But what about an opportunity like this?
可是這麼樣子一個機會呢
Special thanks to Academician Zhang
特別要感謝張院士
Academician Zhang didn’t just bring me into Academia Sinica
張院士呢不只是把我給帶進中央研究院
Even I was able to go to Nanke because of him
甚至於我能夠到南科也是因為他的緣故
1987 Separate Go
民國87年Separate Go
His Separate Go, he went to England
他的Separate Go他到英國去
He told me before you left
你走之前呢他就跟我說
Come and help me lead this project of Nanke
來你幫忙帶帶這個南科的這個計畫
Then I said how do I bring a plan?
那我說我怎麼帶計畫呢
He said you don't need a plan
他說你不用帶計畫
This already has our team over there
這個已經有我們的團隊在那邊
In fact, this leadership of my program for that year
那事實上我在那一年的計畫的這個領導
It's not called a leader, it's actually called a cup of NTD from Nangang to Tainan
不叫領導,事實上是叫做杯新台幣從南港到台南
I got this kind of treatment very generously
我得到了非常豐厚的這種待遇
Yes as soon as they see me arriving they know I have money
是只要他們看到我到了就知道我有鈔票
Because at that time I was the one who took the check and went to the Farmer's Bank to collect NT dollars
因為那時候是我拿的支票到農民銀行去領了新台幣
Then I packed it in the bag with the camera
然後我是拿著照相機的袋子裝了
Then when they got on the plane they thought it was a camera
然後搭飛機的時候他們以為裡面是照相機
But I also know they probably know what's in there
可是我也知道他們可能知道裡面是什麼
It's not a camera, because the shadow of a camera is different
不是照相機,因為照相機的影子不一樣
Then I should say that if there is not such a chance
那我應該說如果不是有這麼樣子一個機會
Then it is not because of this distribution of Nanke archaeological sites
然後不是因為有南科考古遺址的這個分布
So I have seen what Mr. Zhang said
所以已經看到了張先生所說的
What is more important is a distribution like this
那更重要的是這個樣子的一個分布呢
This completely subverts the cognition of Taiwan's archaeological circles
整個顛覆了台灣考古學界的這個認知
Frankly speaking, before the 1995 Republic of China
坦白的說民國95年之前
Not before 1995 in 1995
不是民國84年 1995年之前
No ruins have ever been found in this park.
這個園區裡面一個遺址也不曾發現過
I used to follow Mr. Zhang
我曾經跟著張先生的是
Let's go to the outer ring road of Naner Gao
我們去做南二高的外環道
The middle of the outer ring road is relatively close
外環道的中間裡面比較靠近的
A site called Kanxi
一個叫看溪的這個遺址
on the periphery of the park
是在園區的外圍
In other words, the entire park
換句話說整個園區裡面
Among the more than 70 ruins discovered so far
目前所發現的七十幾個遺址裡面
Didn't know any before 1995
在1995年之前一個也不知道
So at a mileage like this
所以在這樣子的一個里程下
This archaeological excavation work in the entire Nanke Park
整個南科園區的這個考古發掘工作
Transformed Taiwan's archaeological circles
化下了台灣考古學界
In particular what we call contract archeology
特別是我們叫做contract archeology
such a mission
這麼樣子的一個使命
Also found so many of these ruins
也發現了這麼多的這些遺址
So these decades
所以這十數年來
I frankly say that I am half a Taipei native
我坦白說我半個台北人
I started on July 1, 2007
我從2007年7月1號開始
I have two to three days a week
我每個禮拜有兩天到三天的時間
lived in Tainan
是在台南過的
So I think a ban like this
所以我想這麼樣子的一個禁遇
give me a lot of this opportunity
讓我很很多的這種機會
not just academically
不只是在學術上
in work management
在工作的管理上面
The whole thing got me a lot of these
整個都讓我有很多的這些
accumulation of experience
經驗的累積
In fact, I can also take this opportunity
那事實上我也可以藉著這個機會
Come to the courtyard, come to the office
來跟院裡面 來跟所裡面
even in my own home
甚至於我自己的家裡面
to illustrate over the years
來說明這麼多年來
I'm such a crackpot
我這麼樣子的一個崩潑
or
或者是
The high-speed rail should give me some briefings, right?
高鐵都應該給我一些講狀吧
good
好
Speaking of which, I still want to give you an idea first.
那說到這我還是要先給各位概念
That is to say, the so-called 5,000 years of Taiwan mentioned earlier
就是說剛剛已經先提的所謂的台灣五千年
Taiwan's 5,000-year history
台灣歷史五千年
Mr. Zhang mentioned it to you at the beginning
張先生一開始就給各位提的
The United people said that Taiwan originally had no history
聯合人說的台灣原本沒有史
There is only 400 years of history from the Henan people
有史從河南人開始不過四百年
But here we want to talk to you
可是我們這邊卻要跟各位談
We have literally five thousand years of history
我們有確確實實的五千年的歷史
what about this
那這個呢
or so he said
或者是他也這麼講了
If you want to convey a concept like this to
你如果想要把這樣子的一個概念貫輸給
He already had some knowledge of Taiwan's history
他原本已經對台灣的歷史有所認知的
He already told you to lie
他已經說你你騙一下
but the fact is not
可是事實不然
From the accumulations inside the archaeological site, we
我們從考古遺址裡面的堆積裡面
I can tell you
確確實實可以告訴各位
The Nanke Archaeological Site Group has accumulated
南科考古遺址群累積了
Some history of Taiwan over the past 5,000 years
台灣五千年來的一些歷史
so many years
這麼多年來
We found more than 2,000 of these sticks
我們發現了兩千多具的這些木杖
I'm not going to lie to you
我不瞞各位說
I often tell a lot of people in society
我經常會跟很多的社會大眾也講
Wherever I go, maybe half of them will follow me
我走到哪裡搞不好有一半的就跟著我走
Maybe you're next door
說不定你們隔壁的
And those who followed you next to each other
還有那些跟著你們一起挨著做的
This is what I told the Nanke Park Administration
這個也是我跟南科園區管理局這麼說了
I said I have been so ten years
我說我這麼十多年來
What you see is fantasy
看到的是物幻心儀人事非
But more than 2,000 of these from 5,000 to 300 years
可是兩千多具的這些從五千年一直到三百年
What about these grain trees in the past few years?
在這幾年來的這些穀木呢
Their souls have been running on it
他們的魂呢,一直在上面跑
I even sometimes
我甚至於有的時候
I wish I could tell them
我恨不得我就跟他們說
The roof of your building is very black
你們的樓頂上特別的黑
then you'll know what that is
那你們就知道那是什麼了
ok that
好,那
In fact, one of the biggest benefits of
事實上這裡面最大的一個好處
what we found
我們所發現到的
It's not just that there are many chairs, it's the same thing
不只是椅子多,椅子多是一回事情
it is in very good condition
它保存的狀況非常良好
It seems that we can clearly
於似乎我們可以很清楚地
to find its source
去找到它的來榮去墨
its long
它的時間長
its time complete
它的時間完整
Even we have a lot of
甚至於我們有非常多的
these kinds of diversity
這些各種不同的這些多樣性
So it seems that what I want to tell you
於似乎我想要跟各位講的
From some clusters of chairs that look like this
我們從這麼樣子的一些椅子群裡面
we are talking about environmental change
我們是在談環境變遷
let's talk about ecological adaptation
我們來談生態適應
We talk about social structures , we talk about living crafts and technologies
我們談社會結構,我們談生活工藝與技術
Even when we talk about life should be and faith, etc.
甚至於我們談生命理應跟信仰等等的
These issues are what give us the opportunity to get to know Taiwan
這些議題才是讓我們有機會來認識台灣
I have known Taiwan for so many years
認識台灣這麼多年來
How are these people living here?
怎麼樣子的這些人在這邊來活著
Just now Mr. Zhang also mentioned
剛剛張先生也提到
Taiwan has been inhabited here since 30,000 years ago
台灣從3萬年前開始有人在這邊居住
But inside a pair of glasses at such a time
可是這麼樣子的一個時間的一個眼鏡裡面
From the old era to the new era
從舊時期時代一直到新時期時代
to the Iron Age to the early Han Chinese
到鐵器時代到早期的漢人
when you come here
到這邊來的時候
In fact, we still have a lot of gaps that we don't understand clearly
事實上我們還有一些很多不理解不清楚的一些空白
in other words
換句話說
tell you
跟各位講
I specially drew a red circle here
我這邊特別畫了一個紅色的圓圈
sorry
對不起
If this is in your history textbook
這裡如果是在各位的歷史教科書裡面
there will be a witness
會有一個佐證人
The witness also claimed to have a time of 30,000 years ago
佐證人當時也號稱有三萬年前的時間
But recently
可是最近
One of our colleagues was originally a student of mine
我們的一個同事原本是我的學生
Teacher at Tsinghua University
清華大學的老師
As a result, only three thousand years were withdrawn as witnesses.
結果撤出來佐證人只有三千年
Originally, Mayor Lai wanted to take that specimen back.
原先賴市長還想把那個標本給要回去
I think now he doesn't want it either
我想現在他也不想要了
good
好
Another fact I want to mention to you is that
另外一個事實是要跟各位提的是
From the Changbing Culture 30,000 years ago
從三萬年前的長兵文化
until the new period we now know
一直到我們現在所知道的新時期
Early Age Crash
時代早期的大崩坑
We have no specific archaeological accumulations in this period
這段中間裡面我們沒有具體的考古的堆積
This also shows that this group of people in the early days of the new era
這也是說明了新時期時代早期的這一群人
Not this group of people from Changbing culture
並不是從長兵文化的這一群人
a continuation of life
整個生活生命的一個延續
This continuation of life comes from
生活的這種延續而來的
Under such an understanding
在這樣子的一個理解下
i want to tell you
我想跟各位講
When did Taiwan become Taiwan?
台灣什麼時候變成台灣
this question is difficult to answer
這個問題很難回答
Did someone say you were talking about politics?
有人說你是在談政治嗎
I don't hide from you
我也不瞞各位說
I was once inside the opportunity where the minister of culture led a group of journalists
我曾經在文化部長帶著一群記者的機會裡面
I asked them the same question
我問了他們同樣的一個問題
Some say tens of millions of years, millions of years
有人說好幾千萬年,好幾百萬年
I said when did Taiwan leave a connection with mainland China
我說台灣什麼時候離開了中國大陸的一個connection
Many people are stupid over there
很多人就傻在那邊
18,000 years ago, Taiwan could still use roads and bridges to walk
18000年前的時候,台灣還可以用走的經過路橋
Arrive in mainland China
到達中國大陸
But in fact by 8000 years
可是事實上到了8000年的時候
The Taiwan Strait has been formed
台灣海峽就已經形成了
If this understanding is correct when
如果這個理解是正確的時候
After 8000 years, there is no such fact that 8000 years have come to Taiwan
8000年以後,現在並沒有8000年來到台灣的這種事實
archaeological evidence
考古證據
In the early days of the New Reality Era, within our 5,6000 years
新實際時代早期,我們5、6000年的時間裡面
what must this group of people be like
這群人一定是什麼樣
Is it enough
夠不夠
slipping slipping slipping boat
滑著滑著滑著船的
Otherwise, it's swimming
不然的話就是游泳游過來的
In fact it is impossible
事實上也不可能
In such an understanding
在這樣子的一個理解
Let's look back at our Nanke Yuan District
我們再回頭來看我們的南科遠區
In this more than 2000 hectares
在這2000多公頃的
stacked inside
堆積裡面
It also provides some process of our whole environment change
它也提供了我們整個環境變遷的一些過程
I want to tell you
想要跟各位說的
This is what Mr. Zhang just mentioned
這個是剛剛張先生已經提到的
Nanke in 1995
1995年的南科
yes
是
Cemetery
墓廠
Inano Cemetery
稻野墓廠
Inano Farm
稻野農廠
The whole thing is so dry
整個都是這種乾澈的
There is another western orifice
這裡面有另外的一個西竅
because they are burden bearers
是因為他們是重擔者
so
所以
A lot of chairs never get a chance to be flipped open first
很多的椅子從來沒有機會被翻開來先開過
Because you planted this is only a shallow root, forty or fifty centimeters
因為你種乾這只是淺根,四五十公分
they can just plant
他們就可以就種了
Well, Nanke in 2012 is a sight like this
好,2012年的南科是這個樣子的一個景象
you can imagine
你可以去想像
A change in the environment of the entire southwestern coast of Taiwan
整個台灣西南海岸環境的一個變遷
what will it be like
會是一個什麼樣子的一個模像
When I was really straight
當初在真直的時候
Some people even say that it is impossible to find the ruins in this place
甚至於有人說這個地方不可能發現遺址的
Why?
為什麼?
Because it was originally in a water environment
因為它當初是在一個水域環境裡面
This understanding is not bad
這個理解並不錯
If you look at this map
你如果拿這一張地圖來看
This is a map of city descendants, an elevated map of city descendants
這個是一個市裔圖,標高的市裔圖
At certain times the entire park is
在某些時間裡面整個園區都
Still in the water environment
還是在水域的環境裡面
We make from many places
我們從很多的地方制
Taiwan restrictions Many restrictions
台灣限制 諸多限制裡面
can be found
都可以去發現到
They also had records saying
他們當時還有記錄說
The whole big ship can go all the way here
整個大船能夠一直開到這裡
In a location where the so-called Newport is located
所謂的新港所在的一個位置上
Okay, this is what Mr. Zhang just showed to everyone
好 這個是剛剛張先生秀給大家看
Our Sanjin is still doing it in the middle of the night
我們三金半夜還在做
Not called Sanjin Midnight
不叫三金半夜
In fact at that time
事實上那個時候
do it from 7:30 in the morning
做的是從早上七點半
until half past ten in the evening
一直到晚上十點半
Chi Mei, but it's not called Chi Mei anymore
奇美 不過現在已經不叫奇美
This is what happened
這個就是這個事過境
Innolux
現在叫群創
they asked us
他們當時要求我們
It means a loss of 100 million a day
是說一天一億的損失
if we can afford it
如果我們付得起的話
But archeology can have 100 million
但考古的能夠有1億
I think maybe Mr. Zhang also has a clue.
我想大概張先生也是有把
he sold several
他賣好幾張
can't sell the house
房子都卖不出来
good
好
This is the current surface
这个是现在的地表
what about this ruins
这个遗址呢
In this way, there are seven meters
这么样子下来有七公尺生
everybody
各位
you can then
你就可以当时
when we were doing exploration
我们在做探勘的时候
you can find
就可以发现到
such a deep pile
这么深的一个堆积
in other words
换句话说
five thousand years
五千年来
Its a stack of seven meters
它的一个堆积七公尺生
If a change in the entire geographical environment
如果按整个地理环境的一个变迁
such a data
这样子一个数据
The data is also very fast
数据也是非常的一个快的
we follow
我们跟着
One of Mr. Chen Wenshan's
陈文山老师的一个
Under the synergy
协同之下
He made a transfer of the entire address
他进行了整个地址的转判
Judgment and Restoration of the Coastline
判判以及海岸线的复原
That let us also find out
那让我们也发现到了
A location where the entire circle is located
整个圆区所在的一个位置
would happen to be near a coastline where it was 5,000 years ago
正好會是距今5000年前所在的一個海岸線的附近
So we can clearly understand
所以我們可以清楚地去認知到了
From a change in the entire coastal environment
從整個海岸環境的一個變遷裡面
until 6000 years ago
一直到了6000年前的時候
The entire Nanke Park is still in the water
整個南科園區都還在水域裡面
By the year 5000 we started to enter
到了5000年我們開始幅入了
Just now Mr. Zhang also explained
剛剛張先生也說明了
Because there is Zeng Wenxi in the north and Yanshuixi in the south
因為北邊有曾文熙 南邊有岩水熙
There is a river shortfall on the west coast of Taiwan
台灣的西岸得一個河川短處
and when it rains
而且即降雨的時候
It can bring a large amount of sediment to accumulate very quickly
它可以帶了大量的泥沙很迅速地堆積上來
in fact here
事實上說到這裡
I also want to share with you a piece of news like this
還想跟各位透露一個 這麼樣子的一個消息
what commonday magazine did
天下雜誌所做的
You know what problem we are facing now
各位知道我們現在所面臨的一個什麼問題
Global warming, this is a fact, a geologist in Australia in 1993, what he did would cause a sea level rise of three centimeters every year
全球暖化,這個是事實,1993年澳洲的一位地質學家,他所做的每一年會有三公分的海平面的上升
If you start with a count rate like this, if you flood 6 meters, 15 meters, 25 meters, everyone knows that this is a balance
如果就這麼樣子的一個數率來開始的時候,淹了6公尺,15公尺,25公尺,各位都知道這個是有衡
If you have a sense of crisis when you see this, I will show you this again
如果看到這個有危機意識的時候,各位我再給各位看這個
In 2080, Wonsan Hotel, probably I know that when you go out, the second thing is to call Wonsan Hotel immediately, if there is any space above the tenth floor, you can just buy it
2080年的時候,元山飯店,大概我知道等一下你們走出門,第二件事馬上打電話問問元山飯店,第十層樓以上的有還沒有空間,可以恰購
It was 2080, Wonsan Hotel probably knew the current situation, now it is 2080, Wonsan Hotel probably knew the current situation, you can just buy
是2080年的時候,元山飯店,大概知道現在的情況,現在是2080年的時候,元山飯店,大概知道現在的情況,可以恰購
2010 101
2010年的101
of course i will say
當然我會說
In 2080
2080年的時候
i'm on the mountain behind
我在後面的山上
wave with everyone
跟著大家揮手
good
好
then this is one
那這個就是一個
environmental change
環境變遷
a difference in rate
數率的一個不同
everybody
各位
one like this
那這麼樣子的一個
under the concept
概念之下
Let's see Nanke
我們來看南科
Nanke for so many years
南科這麼多年來
let us
讓我們
know
所知道的
From 5000 until
從5000年一直到
Late entry
晚進的
Two or three hundred years
兩三百年
even
甚至於
we can see
我們可以看得到
the last 20 years
最近的這20年
all the whole
所有的整個
a change in the environment
環境的一個變遷裡面
people coming and going
人來人往
what did we see
我們看到了什麼
5000 years ago
5000年前
I want to give you
我想要給各位
look first
先看看
Naughty Supply's Technology
淘氣供應的技術
a change of
的一個改變
Everyone too
各位也
if you have a concept
如果你有概念的時候
you can all understand
你們都可以去理解
In the early century era Dabunkeng culture was fascinated by Wentao
在世紀時代早期大奔坑文化出神溫陶
One of their trances Wen Tao
他們的一個出神溫陶
It is just a feature of the appearance and shape of a whole pottery
只不過是一個整個陶器的外觀形制上面的一個特徵而已
actually real content
實際上真正的內容
one of its appearance
它的一個外觀形制
how does it do
它怎麼做的
What kind of soil is it made of?
用什麼樣子的一個土做出來的
What kind of technology was used to develop it?
用什麼樣子的一個技術去發展出來的
This is what we really want to understand
這個才是我們真正希望去理解的
You can also see a variety of
你也可以去看得到各種各式各樣的
Except for the god Wentao
除了出的神溫陶之外
its shape
它的形制
this is a bean
這個是一個豆
This is Chai Tao
這個是柴陶
This chai pottery is not the most primitive and recognized one
這個柴陶就不是最原始被認知的一個
one of the cultural characteristics
文化特徵裡面的一個
Even from an element like this, we can
甚至於我們就可以從這麼樣子的一個要素裡面
to understand the inner relationship of its culture
來理解它的文化的內緣關係
this is a gas cap
這個是一個氣蓋
This is covered by a shell of blood and sweat
這上面的是一個血汗的殼所蓋上來
Remember Academician Zhang Guangze
還記得張光澤院士
A theory put forward by Academician Zhang Guangze
張光澤院士他所提的一個理論
He from a decorative document like this
他從這麼樣子的一個裝飾文事上面
To illustrate the top of the Phu Quocton ruins in Kinmen
來說明金門的富國敦遺址上面
He also explained the same
有同樣的他也說明了
This may have a relationship above the Culture class circle relationship
這可能有文化類圓關係上面的一個關係
Well, four thousand years ago
好 到了四千年前
Guys, on our archaeological culture
各位 在我們的考古文化上面
We call it Xishen Wentao
我們稱它為細神文陶
Or call it Shenwen red pottery culture
或者是叫它神文紅陶文化
but you can find out
可是你可以去發現到
The whole appearance situation has changed
整個外觀形勢改變了
We even found four sticks
甚至於我們也發現到了有四個木杖
We call it "Hongguan"
我們稱它為《弘關》
Here is the child's body
這裡面裝的是小朋友的body
children's shares
小朋友的股
inside
在裡面
This is also the earliest in Taiwan
這也是目前在台灣年代最早的
A record of this "Hongguan"
這個《弘關》的一個記錄
We can even see a variety of
我們甚至於可以看得到各種各式各樣的
But you obviously you can find out
可是你明顯的你可以去發現到
It is the same as the 5000 years ago
它跟5000年前的
are different
是不一樣的
good
好
this is an escape
這個是一個逃脫
Also stated let us know they made the escape themselves
也說明了讓我們知道他們自己來製作逃棄
A legacy of such a tool
的這麼樣的一個工具的一個遺留
The Great Lakes culture to 3000 years ago
到了3000年前的大湖文化
You can see it right away
你馬上一眼下來你就可以看到了
it's black
它是黑的
so red hot red
所以紅的燒紅的
This technique changes to slightly horizontal black
這個技術改變到稍橫黑的
Then how do you think about it?
那這裡面你會怎麼樣去思考
it's a group of people
它是一群人呢
A different group of people came here
還是不同的群的人來到了這邊
What makes us depressed is how come
是讓我們壓抑的是怎麼來
why come
為什麼來
Until the Iron Age 2000 years ago
一直到了2000年前的鐵器時代
What kind of red color has the whole process technology changed into?
整個的工藝技術又轉變成什麼紅顏色的
And you can find out
而且各位你也可以去發現到了
Is it one of their crafting techniques?
是不是他們的一個工藝技術
has slowly declined
已經慢慢的沒落了
What a change
還是怎麼樣子的一個轉變
red to black
紅的到黑的
black to red
黑的到紅的
Even the whole appearance is different.
甚至於整個的外觀形制都不一樣了
This is even the gas cap you can find, the same as the gas cap from 5,000 years ago
這個都是連氣蓋你都可以發現跟五千年前的那種氣蓋
The air cap from 5,000 years ago is inside our life now
五千年前的氣蓋在我們現在的生活裡面
can also see the very common air-shaped
都還能夠看得到非常普遍的那些氣形的
We can even find that as far as the Iron Age
我們甚至於可以發現到鐵器時代的時候
A gaseous shape characteristic of the symbol of this puppet
特有的這種陶偶的象徵的一個氣形
More than 500 years ago, we thought it belonged to
到了五百多年前的我們認為是屬於
Inside a legacy of Hirayan culture
希拉雅文化的一個遺留裡面
The most important thing is that they still retain the iron age
最重要的是他們仍保有如同鐵器時代
The making of soft pottery of Niaosong culture
鳥松文化的那種軟陶的製作
At the same time they also have a lot of these from mainland China
同時他們也有了非常多的這些從中國大陸
There are also some from Southeast Asia
也有一部分從東南亞
There is also this one from Kyushu Feitian, Japan
也有從日本九州肥田的這個
One of these mischievous remnants of shaker making
搖子所製作出來的這些淘氣的一個遺留
These are all explained
這些都一一的說明了
These people who live in Tainan at the same time
同時住在台南的這些人
How are you from other places?
怎麼樣子的跟外地
interact with one of their living environments
跟他們的一個生活環境互動
The evidence that remains
所遺留下來的這些證據
Well, these people from 5,000 years ago
好 五千年前的這些人
let us know
讓我們知道的是
They are likely to be heavily dependent on
他們很可能是大量的依賴
marine resources food resources
海洋性資源 食物資源的人群
Why because from what remains of our animal bones
為什麼 因為從我們動物骨格的遺留裡面
We found that there are a large number of
我們發現到了有大量的
These numbers of boruids exceed those of land-based
超過於陸地的博魯類動物的這些數量的
what remains of these fish
這些魚的遺留
in our knowledge
在我們的見識裡面
We found three different species of these cartilaginous fish
我們發現到了三種不同的這些軟骨魚類
For example, a shark's, a fish's, a bite, a giant bite
比方說鯊魚的 烘魚的 咬 巨咬
Nineteen species of bony fishes
有十九種的硬骨魚類
These are actually us
這些呢 實際上是我們
make real professional
讓真正的專業的
helped us identify
幫著我們來鑑定的
for example this
比方說這個
This is in our earliest cognition
這個在我們最早的認知裡面
Thought it was going to be this head of an amphibian
以為會是兩棲動物的這個頭顱
Turns out it was a shark
結果後來發現到了是鯊鯊魚
This is this fish near the mouth of the river
這是河海口附近的這個魚類
This is what we found out last year
這是去年我們才發現到的
We first called it mangosteen
這個我們最早我們稱它為山竹起
i traveled all over europe
我走遍了歐洲
Go to France, to Germany, to Japan, to the United States to ask what this is
到法國、到德國、到日本、到美國去問問這個是什麼
As a result no one can recognize
結果沒有人可以認知
We even got the University of York in the UK to do puthi for us
我們甚至於讓英國的約克大學幫我們做普提
But the analysis of white matter seems to want to know what the animal would look like
但白質的分析似乎想要去知道到底會是什麼樣子的動物
It turned out that last year an assistant at the Museum of Marine Biology
結果去年一位原本在海洋生物博物館的一個助理
He went to Belgium to study his doctorate
他到比利時去念他的博士學位
He told us that this is a monitoring department in Huiqingjiao
他告訴我們這個是灰青角的一個監聞部
Everyone, this animal was beaten by humans
各位這個動物是人打的
In other words, after they hit these fish
換句話說他們打了這些魚之後
They also used one of his supervisory news departments as a supervisory news department
他們還把他的一個監聞部拿來當作是一個監聞部
a decoration to use
一個裝飾品來使用
good
好
except fish
除了魚類之外
they use a lot
他們大量的使用
shellfish
貝類
We were five thousand years ago
我們在五千年前的
South Guan Li Dong Healing Inside
南關里東醫治裡面
have more than
有超過
Seventy-seven different kinds of these shellfish
七十七種不同的這些貝類
good
好
how do we learn about these shellfish
我們怎麼樣子來瞭解這些貝類
Director Wang is here
這個汪處長在這邊
i want to take this opportunity
我要藉這個機會
Special thanks also to Director Wang
也要特別謝謝汪處長
President Wang Teacher Wang
汪總統汪老師
When I was doing my doctoral thesis
我自己在做博士論文的時候
make shellfish
做貝類
In addition to identification
除了鑑定之外
We do the analysis of probing isotopes
我們做探養同位素的分析
Analysis of Probe Isotopes
探同位素的分析
To understand the water environment
來瞭解水域環境
Analysis of trophic isotopes
養同位素的分析
To understand the temperature of the water body
來瞭解水體的溫度
That is to say, from the temperature of the water body
也就是說從水體的溫度
let's find out
我們來瞭解
when were these shellfish caught
這些貝類是什麼時候去抓的
when did you step on it
什麼時候去踩的
because shellfish when he was alive
因為貝類當他活著的時候
every day he grows
每一天他都會有生長
one of his growth
他的一個生長文
while growing
生長的同時
he will record
他都會記錄下
A content of the aquatic environment of his life history
他生命史水域環境的一個內容
good
好
from Nanguanli
從南關里
This is a statistical analysis of Yuzi in Nanguanli
這個是南關里魚子的一個統計分析裡面
we found
我們發現到了
This so-called Ke Wenhai Scroll
這個所謂的柯文海捲
Internet Scroll
網路海捲
Can you find out
各位可不可以去發現
This is like what we are eating now
這個就好像我們現在在吃的
Chick Ray's body type
小雞雷一樣的一個體型
I even want to tell you
甚至於我要告訴各位
five thousand years
五千年來
eat this chick ray
吃這種小雞雷
or the so-called sea rolls
或者是所謂的這些海捲
method is the same
方法都是一樣的
just put that head
就是把那個頭
remove and suck
給去掉 然後一吸
Yes or no
是不是
Everyone should have experience with this hat.
各位應該還有這帽子的一個這個經驗吧
In particular, let me explain to you
特別再跟各位說明一下
this is
這個就是
I want to talk to you
跟要跟各位講
We all live in a test room
我們都生活在考屋裡
Apart from eating shellfish, these people
這些人除了吃貝之外
They even used those shells as tools
他們甚至於把那些貝殼拿來當工具的使用
This is an extinct window
這個是已經絕滅的一個窗戴
or Yunmuge
或者是叫雲木格
Besides eating shells, they
他們除了吃了貝殼以外
In addition to eating shellfish
除了吃了貝肉之外
Shells are also used as shell knives
貝殼還拿來當作貝刀來使用
You can see these sentences
各位可以看得到這些句詞文
we have asked
我們曾經請教過
an archaeologist who specializes in this oceania
專門研究這個大洋洲的一位考古學家
he came to tell us
他來告訴我們說
This is likely to be in
這個很可能是在
It is a tool for removing the skin of sweet potatoes and sweet potatoes like this kind of follow-up
就是消跟進類的這種做地瓜番薯這些的一個皮的一個工具
In addition to eating and using them, everyone also uses them as a water product for wooden sticks
各位除了吃除了用他們還拿來當作木杖的一個伴水品
We even think that its probable representative social status
我們甚至於認為這些它很可能的有代表的社會地位
They even have so-called symbols of faith
他們甚至於有所謂的信仰的象徵
Why? Most of the time we see only five thousand years ago.
為什麼呢?很多時候我們看到的五千年前的這隻也只有在五千年前才有的
They put shells on top of their ears and noses
他們把貝殼放在耳鼻上面
They made a lot of these shells as an ornament
他們做了不少的這些貝殼的一個裝飾品
The analysis of carbon and oxygen isoples we performed
我們進行的碳氧同位數的分析
Want to understand from 5000 years, 4000 years, 3000 years, 2000 years
想要理解的從5000年、4000年、3000年、2000年
These shellfish extant in these ruins until late
一直到晚進的這些遺址裡面所流存的這些貝類
What kind of environment did you grow up in?
到底是生長在什麼樣子的一個環境
What time and season are these communities collecting
到底是什麼時間、什麼季節被這些社群去採集的
Well, this is just a little introduction to you first.
那這個也就是先稍微給各位介紹一下
this is a letter
這個是一個寫函
We go from the top of the shell to this edge of the shell
我們從壳頂一直到壳的這個邊緣
Then every other this distance
然後每隔一個這個一段距離
let's sample it
我們來取它的樣
Take a sample of it and there's something called calcium carbonate in it
取它的樣裡面有所謂的碳酸鈣
give us a chance to extract its carbon and oxygen
讓我們有機會去萃取它的碳跟氧
to understand one of them
來理解他們的一個
A cultivation of the same quality
同位素質的一個養成
Okay, so this is what we started from Dabankeng
好 那這個也就是我們從大半坑
Five thousand years ago to Niuzhou paper
五千年前的到牛州紙
This is about four thousand years old
這個大約四千年的
Let's analyze a sample of it
我們去分析它的一個樣本
to understand in the aquatic environment
來理解在水域環境裡面
So most of the food is in Hehaikou
所以大部分吃的都是在河海口
A remnant closer to a freshwater environment
比較靠近淡水環境的一個遺留
This is from the Great Lakes Culture and the Bird Culture
這個是大湖文化跟鳥中文化的
A comparison of what we see when
一個比較的時候我們所看到的
They are almost all in the same water environment.
那幾乎都是同樣的一個水域環境裡面
Even Sheila's
甚至於希拉雅的
So our observation like this
所以我們這麼樣子的一個觀察裡面
we are accompanied by the present
我們伴隨著目前
what we can collect
我們所可以收集到的
These records of temperature and rainfall in the southwestern waters of Taiwan
台灣西南海域的氣溫跟雨量的這些記錄
let's see it
我們來看它
some of their variations
他們的一些變化
And then comparing these different seasons that we're seeing
然後在對照著我們所看到的這些不同季節
One oxygen composition of all these carbon-oxygen isotopes
所有的這些碳氧同位素質的一個氧成
So in an analysis like this
所以在這樣子的一個分析裡面
we can find out
我們可以去發現到
A distance from the Nanke ruins where it is now
現在所在的南科遺址的一個距離
with the coastline
跟海岸線
In fact, a change in the water environment is not big
實際上水域環境的一個變化並不大
is very similar
就是非常類似
But we found
可是我們卻發現到了
Like, say, this is a telescope screw
像比方說這個是望遠鏡螺
This is mangrove insurance
這是紅樹險
this is blood and sweat
這是血汗
This is window north is extinct
這是窗北都已經滅絕了
Is that man-made or a change in the environment?
那到底是人為的還是環境的一個變化
One of the resources responsible for these multipliers
造成這些倍率的資源的一個
We started with these Taiwanese assistants who entered the latest
我們從最晚進的這些台灣輔治
Inside a map from about four hundred years ago
大約四百年前的地圖裡面
can also be found
也可以去發現到
A change in the environment of these waters
這些水域環境的一個變化
with what we see now
跟我們現在所看到的
that way
那這麼一來
we can also understand
我們也可以去理解到
Inland it contributes to the whole environment
地內它對於整個環境的
Sensitivity is likely
敏感程度很可能
not easy enough to give them a chance
不容易讓他們足夠有機會
to adapt and survive
去適應然後流存下來
So especially those types of backs that I just saw
所以尤其是剛剛所看到的那幾種背類
The only difference is
唯一不同的就是
what you know now
各位現在知道的
What is the most famous snack in Taiwan called?
台灣最有名的小吃叫什麼
wow really
哇 真啊
It won't be a small bar
不會是小酒壘啊
I spent two years following Ke Ming of Qigude
我花了兩年的時間跟著七谷德的柯明
There is a man named Conan
有一位叫做柯南的
This Conan belongs to Haiyan Institute of National Taiwan University
這位柯南的還是台大的海岩所的
half read
念到一半
Then I grabbed a few Konuli
然後抓了幾支柯努力
Go to his boss and say I quit
到他的老闆前面說我不幹了
I'm going home to plant Ke
我回家去種柯去
yes
是
But everybody
可是各位
just said that
剛剛這麼樣子說來
In fact, I want to tell you
事實上也就是要跟各位講
a change in the environment
整個環境的一個變化
What is caused is a change in environmental resources
造成的是環境資源的一個變遷
One of the above patterns adapted to humans
跟人類適應上面模式上面的一個
an application of the strategy
策略上面的一個應用
This is what we often think about
這個也是經常我們一直在想
good
好
Four thousand years ago, these shells had spring, summer, autumn, and winter, and they were almost average, which reflected what it might be like. They had shells in spring, summer, autumn and winter, and they were not enough to eat because they were grown by themselves.
四千年前这些贝壳,他们有春天、夏天、秋天、冬天,几乎平均都许,反映的很可能会是什么样,春夏秋冬都要许贝,是自己种的还不够吃。
Four thousand years ago, there were many springs and winters, a little less autumn, and almost no summer.
四千年前的春跟冬特别的多,秋天少一点,夏天几乎没有。
More than 3,000 years ago were also spring, summer, autumn, and winter, so these Han people who came in from 5,000, 4, and 3,000 years until the late arrival,
三千多年前的也是春夏秋冬,所以这么样子下来,从五千年、四千年、三千年一直到晚进的这些汉人,
Living in the same environment in the southwestern waters of Taiwan, how to use these shellfish resources, this is to provide us with a very clear understanding.
住在同样这个台湾西南海域环境里面,怎么样子来利用这些贝类资源,这个就是提供给我们一个非常清楚的一些认识的。
Yes, in fact, in 2004, I was on the first floor of the southwestern waters of Taiwan,
是,我事实上2004年,我这次在台湾西南海域的一层,
At the request of the former vice president Zhu Jinyi and Mr. Zhu
在前副院長朱金一、朱老師的一個要求下
At that time, it seemed that Vice President Wang asked me to write it.
那時候好像也是王副院長要求我寫的吧
Taiwan's first rice and first dog
台灣的第一把米跟第一隻狗
In fact, we also want to thank our teacher Xi
事實上也要謝謝我們習老師
Teacher Xi is the rice and millet that his team gave us the opportunity to really know
習老師是他的團隊讓我們有機會真正認識的這些稻米跟小米
We even recently discovered that there was more than one kind of millet five thousand years ago
我們甚至於最近還發現到了五千年前的小米還不只一種
Let Teacher Xi tell the story behind this
這個後面的故事要讓習老師自己來說了
But the most important meaning is where
不過最重要的一個意義是在於哪裡
when we started school
我們開始念書的時候
twenty years ago thirty years ago
二十年前三十年前
To rice will spread to Taiwan
到米要傳到台灣來
At least after 3000 AD
至少是西元三千年以後
things that can happen
才可能發生的事情
Results of Nanke's Discovery
結果南科的發現
Destroyed all previous acquaintances
摧毀了所有之前的一個認識
This is a very typical
這個就是一個非常典型的
very specific answer
非常具體的一個答案
from different times
從不同時間
five thousand four thousand three thousand
五千年 四千年 三千年
until the latest
一直到最晚進的
We start from the morphometric
我們從形態測量上面
got to know them when
去了解了他們當時候
whatever you want
所欲種的這些
one content on rice left over
稻米遺留上面的一個內容
Take Nanguanli five thousand years ago
就拿南關里五千年前的
with four thousand years ago
跟四千年前的
let's do a comparison
我們來做一個比較
Small grain rice Medium grain rice Large grain rice
小粒米 中粒米 大粒米
Compare it like this
這麼樣子一個比較下來
we can find out
我們就可以發現到了
how about some of them
他們有一些怎麼樣
This means that our own technology allows them to have the development of the whole concept
這個也就是說我們自己的工藝技術是讓他們也有整個概念上面的發展
So we can also infer what kind of species they are planning.
所以我們也可以去推知他們到底預得是什麼樣子的種
These are all things that give us the opportunity to witness the content of agricultural cultivation in Taiwan over the past 5,000 years
這些都是讓我們有機會見證了整個台灣5000年以來農業栽培上面的一個內容
It is the legacy that I mentioned to you just now that there are 2,000 in Nanke and now there are nearly 2,500
是剛剛也跟各位提到南科有2000現在已經將近2500具的這個遺留
These remnants from 5,000 years ago you can see and see is an official form of health care straight limbs and their heads
這些遺留5000年前你可以去看得到的是一個公務形式的養生直肢障他們的頭部
They are all facing south, can you guys find them?
都是朝著南邊,各位可不可以去發現到
such a consistency
這麼樣子的一個一致性
Many times when we go to give speeches in different places
很多時候我們在不同的地方去演講的時候
someone will bring it up
都有人會提出來
So how do they buy it?
那他們到底怎麼買啊?
Was there a paper back needle or a paper blue needle five thousand years ago?
五千年前有紙背針還是紙藍針嗎?
Do you have?
有沒有?
Can anyone tell me how they buy it?
有誰可以跟我講他們怎麼買?
look at the sky
看天空
Come, come, you are already the one you know the most
來來來,你已經那個你最會那個最捧場的
Hurry up and give you something first
先趕快先送你一樣東西
this
這個
Classic magazine helped us out
經典雜誌幫我們出的
Yes, look at the sky, when will it come?
是,看天空,什麼時候來?
I look at it at night, do you buy it at night when you buy it?
我看 晚上看 買的時候都是晚上買嗎
Buy during the day and watch at night
白天買 晚上去看
I'll sort this out when I get back.
這個回去我會整理整理
You are all my providers of this information
你們都是我的這個信息的提供者
At that time, my speech fee will also be taken out.
到時候我的演講費也拿出來
Get it out
懂內的出來好了
ok guys did you see this
好 各位有沒有看到這個
one-on-one
一對一對的
Is this a standard monogamous account?
這是是不是標準的一夫一妻帳
Teacher Li Li Aping
老師 歷歷阿平
How many people are there now?
現在多少人都是要好幾
I didn't say it was you who said it
我沒有講是你說的
ok this is one
好 這個就是一個
But in fact they are different
可是事實上他們也有不同的
More than 80% have very high consistency
百分之八十以上都有一致性非常高的
how do we explain these
那我們怎麼樣子來解釋這些
Surprise or what?
意外的還是什麼樣的
At this time, we sometimes think about whether they are the same group of people
這個時候我們有的時候會思考到底他們是不是同一群人
If it's not when they're in the same group
如果不是他們同一群人的時候
They treat the dead differently
他們用不同的方式來對待這些往生者
We can even see the disturbing
甚至於我們還可以看得到這種擾亂的
if you are more specific
如果說得具體一點的
This one is in the ash pit not in the real male tree
這個是在灰坑裡面不是在真正的公木裡面
The so-called one of their male wood-shaped system above
所謂的他們的一個公木形制上面的
Well, Guanmu already existed five thousand years ago
好 五千年前已經有了觀木
This is the viewing board pressed against this individual
這是觀木板壓在這個個體上面的
So you can also know
所以各位也可以知道
Using wooden coffins is not something we have now
用木棺不是我們現在才有的
Four thousand years ago in Taiwan already had
四千年前在台灣已經有了
four thousand years ago
四千年前的時候
one of their males
他們的一個公木
Jinmu Xingzi is the whole strip
金木行字是整個帶狀的
also face male
也是頭朝男
Health straight limb
養生直肢
The difference is what they already have
不同的是他們已經有了什麼
Bow off
弓關
These bows are key to our understanding
這些弓關我們的理解
two years or younger
兩歲或者是更年輕的
a rational way of doing this
這樣子的一個理義方式
such a life theory
這樣子一個生命理義的
one way of treating
一個對待的一個方式
It's beyond our imagination
也是超乎我們的一個想像
Everyone, in fact, when we discovered
各位事實上當初我們在發覺的時候
never thought what this is
一直不敢認為這個是什麼
Because I haven't seen the bones yet
因為還沒有看到骨頭
We even ran to Echime Hospital
我們甚至於跑到以豈美醫院
Go borrow Potable's X-ray
去借Potable的X-ray
I can't even take a photo
去照也照不出來
As a result, we really
結果到後來我們就真正的
it's clearing slowly
是慢慢慢慢去清
Only found out after clearing
一清了以後才發現
There is indeed a staff
這裏面確實是牧杖
well , 3000 years ago
好,到了3000年前
Guys, can you see it?
各位,你是不是可以看得到的
Each cane is a handful
每一個牧杖都是一小撮一小撮的
three five six eight
三五個,六個,八個
There are adults, there are children
有大人的,有小孩子的
This is for adults, this is for children
這個是大人的,這個是小孩的
But the way their heads are facing
可是他們的頭的朝向
has changed
已經改變了
towards the north
朝的朝向,朝北邊
Even the way of one of their rods
甚至於他們的一個牧杖的方式
After shepherding
牧了之後
above the head, thirty to fifty centimeters
頭的上方,三五十公分
ranging from twenty to thirty centimeters
二三十公分不等的
There's a funerary jar on it
上面有一個陪葬罐
This is also what we had in this era more than 3,000 years ago.
這個也是我們在3000多年前的這個年代裏面的
trees that were able to receive these jars very intact
能夠收到非常完整的這些罐子的樹木
most evidence
最多的一個證據
Everyone can also understand that there are all kinds of different views
各位也可以去理解了 是各種不同的這些厚觀
Not just in the thick
不只是放在厚裡面的
We even found that some are placed on the ground first
我們甚至於發現到有的是先擺在地面上
Then take the pot upside down and the upside down one
然後拿著陶膀upside down那個倒扣的
Well, we even found headless
好 我們甚至於發現到沒有頭的
Some are not accompanied by shells like those five thousand years ago.
有的伴隨的就不如同五千年前的有背殼
There is a back and a back is the kind of necklace with a back
有背有背是有背的這個項鍊項飾的那種的
They reflect men's online crimes
他們卻反映著男性的跟著網罪
women follow interview
女性跟著訪論
Some are different from Yugou and so on.
有的跟著魚溝等等的這麼樣子的一個不同
By the Iron Age, the whole reason for life changed
到了鐵器時代,整個生命理由改變
At this time, one of their barriers
這個時候,他們的一個幕障
Knowledge remains the same, head to the north, straight
知識不變,頭朝北邊,直直
But some of them found
可是有一些他們發現到了
What we found was that he took the pieces of the head first
我們發現到的是,他先把那些頭的碎片
paved on the ground, and then the human individual
鋪成在地底上,然後再把人的個體
put it on top, there is indeed a
放在上面,頭的旁邊確實是有
Peach tube , but no longer what
桃管,可是不再是怎麼樣
Thirty to fifty centimeters above the head, fifty or sixty centimeters high
頭的上方三五十公分,五六十公分高的
this place, above this place
這個地點,這個位置上面
Yes, these are all for us to understand
是,這些都也讓我們去理解了
a change in these cultures
這些文化的一個改變
Is it the difference between people? Or the difference in the whole era?
到底是人的不同呢?還是整個時代的不一樣?
And with
而以
we also found
我們也發現到了
this person
這位人士
His head was given in a clay basin
他的頭被一個陶盆給
put it away
另外放起來
This will be explained to you later
這個後面會跟各位再解釋
this is what we think
這個是我們認為
Another evidence of headhunting
獵頭的另外一個證據
good
好
As here we can find that
像在這裡我們可以發現到的是
He uses
他用
into the limb bones to make this
入的肢骨去製作的這種
Link Force Fishhook
連結勢力魚鉤
accompanied by
伴隨在
next to the individual
個體的旁邊的
in this era
在這個時代裡面
Besides this
除了這種之外呢
They are even accompanied by
他們甚至於伴隨著
ironware
鐵器
the only difference
唯一不同的
bath gas replaced by glassware
玻璃器取代的浴氣
good
好
what's next
接下來呢
Let me introduce one more
再跟各位介紹一個
Taiwan's logistics economy
台灣的物流經濟
Taiwan's logistics economy is not
台灣的物流經濟不是
only now
現在才有的
I often think
我經常會認為
The transportation in Taiwan is inconvenient and inconvenient
台灣的交通不方便不方便到
let me experience it myself
讓我自己去體會到
Just now the dean said that I am in Hengchun
剛剛院長說我在恆春
Yes, when I started working in Hengchun in 1993
是 我從1993年開始去做恆春的時候
at that time
那時候
On the first day, I have to take the train to Kaohsiung to stay overnight.
頭一天還得先搭火車到高雄去住一夜
At six o'clock the next morning, take the Guoguang ship to Hengchun
隔天早上六點鐘去搭國光號到恆春去
Inconvenient
方不方便
really inconvenient
真的不方便
Sometimes I can't catch the Guoguang number
有的時候搭不上那個國光號的
you want to take a wild bike
你要搭野機車
you still worry
你還擔心
near marriage
傍婚交啊
yes
是
But
可是
you never thought
你萬萬沒有想到
Logistics in Taiwan started five thousand years ago
台灣的物流在五千年前
surprise you
讓你有驚訝的
scheming
出目心機 驚心的
this is my favorite
這個我最喜歡
It's not this bullshit
這絕不是這個瞎扯的
you guys know what this is
各位知道這是甚麼
Taiwan domain
台灣域
Is it everywhere in Taiwan?
台灣到處都有嗎
Where
哪裡有
Clam
蛤
who said the wind
誰說風權的
The one I can't post here
我這邊發不出去的那個
basically for you
基本給你
come on and write
來等一下來寫
Thanks
謝謝
good
好
How did the domain of Fengtian reach Tainan five thousand years ago
五千年前風田的域怎麼到台南
sorry i should have brought it to you
抱歉我應該拿給你
Thanks
謝謝
how come thank you
怎麼來謝謝
yes
是
domain arrow
域的箭頭
domain collapse
域的崩
The one on the far right lets call it
最右邊的這個叫我們叫它為
Although basalt
雖然是玄武岩
certainly
當然
Teacher Chen Wenshan is not here, he scolds us every time
陳文山老師不在這邊,他每次都罵我們
Why do you choose Wuyan when you see an infection, and you think it’s from Penghu?
為什麼看到感染時選五顏,你們就認為是澎湖來的
How did Penghu come here five thousand years ago?
澎湖來的,五千年前澎湖怎麼來?
You're so loud, so brave, give you one
你那麼大聲,這麼勇敢,趕快給你一個
Thank you, let you get to know Brother Nan better when I go home
謝謝你,回家讓你多認識一下南哥
Well, how did these baths from 5,000 years ago come to Tainan?
好,五千年前的這些浴怎麼到台南這邊來?
It doesn't matter. Four thousand years ago, people were still doing bathing?
這還不打緊,四千年前還是做浴奔呢?
They still have baths, but what?
這個他們還是有浴奔,可是有了什麼?
What about the bath rings? How about all of them?
浴環呢?一個個都在怎麼樣?
How is it still clear?
清清楚楚的就還在怎麼樣?
still above his elbow
還在他的手肘上面
yes
是
3000 years ago
到了3000年前
Wow
哇
This string, this string, we want this and that
這一串這一串我們要這樣那個
see how much
見價多少
yes
沒錯
5000 years 4000 years 3000 years
5000年 4000年 3000年
This group of people live on the southwest coast of Taiwan
這群人住在臺灣西南海岸
how did they come
他們怎麼來
How come there are these so-called
怎麼有這些所謂的
Toyota from Hualien
從花蓮的豐田
come these baths
而來的這些浴
pretty
漂亮吧
These really make us
這些確實讓我們
very surprised
非常訝異的
Are they a group of people?
他們到底是有一群人
specialized in these trades
專門從事的這些貿易的
There is another group of people who specialize in
另外有一群人專門從事
The people who made these crafts
製作的這些工藝技術的人
Or do they know how to find these people themselves?
還是說他們自己懂得去找這些人
for exchange
來進行交易所換的
Of course they are so-called noble artifacts
那當然他們是所謂的尊貴的一些器物
Absolutely we can believe
絕對我們可以去相信
I just showed you this
剛剛給各位看的這個
This is also found in the ruins of "Shanbaopi"
這個也是在《山寶皮》遺址裡面所發現到的
like this individual above
像這個個體上面
Two or three hundred of these pre-tube beads
兩三百顆的這個預管珠
Speaking of which
說到這裡
I also want to introduce to you
還要跟各位介紹一個
Just now the dean also mentioned
剛剛院長也提到了
Mr Zhang also mentioned
張先生也提到了
Taiwan as an Austronesian Aboriginal
台灣作為一個南島原住民
a base on which the nation resides
民族所在的一個基地上面
Mr. Zhang Guangzhi
張光直先生
in 1987
在1987年的時候
He wrote very clearly
他就寫了非常清楚的
In an article like this
這麼樣子一個文章裡面
described
所敘述到了
On the traceability of the South Island
在南島的溯源上面
From the perspective of the garden-like relationship of culture
我們從文化的類園關係上面
what can we discover
我們可以去發現到什麼
rental dog for hunting
租機狗從事狩獵
Make naughty, make columns, etc.
製作淘氣 編習編欄等等
come down like this
這麼樣子下來的
with seafaring technology and with barkcloth
有航海的技術 有樹皮布
Wait, there are rice and millet ones
等等的 有稻米 有小米的
is from the above
是 從上面所說的
everybody
各位
vaguely should be able to understand
依稀的應該還可以去理解到
Taiwan as a
台灣作為一個
A Yuan Township of Minamishimabara Democracy
南島原民主的一個元鄉
doesn't seem too much
似乎並不為過
1910 1910
1910年 1910年的
In a record of Ugly Nosuke
生醜之助的一個記錄裡面
he can see
他可以看得到
This is definitely not Wu Feng's story
這個絕對不是吳鳳的故事
Well, the scene that the Dutch saw when they came to Tainan,
好,荷蘭人來到台南所看到的這個景象,
This is what our ornithine culture saw 2000 years ago. A headhunter,
2000年前我們鳥酸文化所看到的這麼樣子一個獵頭的,
These wooden sticks without heads seen 3000 years ago,
3000年前所看到的沒有頭的這些木杖,
and the three fist teeth we saw 5,000 years ago,
以及5000年前我們所看到的三顆拳齒,
They also pierced a hole,
他們還穿個孔,
Teacher Zhang Guangren also thinks that this is all left over from evidence from a headhunter.
張光仁老師也是認為這個都是一個獵頭的一個證據所遺留下來的,
So 5000 years all the way down,
所以5000年一路下來,
There seems to be a thread,
似乎都有著一個脈絡,
Let us tell us about the inner relationship between these ancestors,
來告訴我們這些先駐明他們之間的這些內緣關係,
Yes or no?
是不是?
and another,
以及另外一個,
a custom of tooth extraction
一個的拔牙的一個風俗
In the material of our national system
在我們的民族制的材料裡面
We can still see and chase
我們現在還可以去看得到追得到的
Explained again and again
再再地都說明了
Did they follow these peoples
他們跟著這些難道民族之間的
a close relationship
一種關係的密切
Bark Cloth Sticks These Faux Wheels
樹皮布打棒這些仿輪
braiding
進行編織編欄
the tools they use
他們所使用的這些的工具
Finally I told you
最後我給各位說了
When did the Han people start coming in?
漢人什麼時候開始進來
The culture of the Han people began to come in in large numbers
漢人的文化開始大量的進來
Definitely not a post-1949 thing
絕對不是1949年以後才有的事
What we saw in Tainan
台南我們所看到的
I used to talk to Tainan's new style
我曾經跟台南新式的
used to be the mayor
以前叫鄉長
I said that the new style used to be outside Taiwan
我說新式曾經是台外
The first place to meet international standards
最早跟國際接軌的地方
He said I was kissing his ass
他說我是拍他馬屁
Teacher Zhu is here
朱老師在這邊喔
Miss Zhu, can you
朱老師你是不是可以
Teacher Zhu is a caring person
朱老師就是心事人
The Heart Has the Earliest Church
心事有最早的教堂
Definitely not Wanhua
絕對不是萬華
Definitely not Wanjin
也絕對不是萬金
Definitely not freshwater
也絕對不是淡水的
ass church
馬屁的教堂
It's something on your mind, right?
而是心事對不對
But I still want to tell you
可是我還要跟各位講
you wait and see
你等等等著看著
an entry into these material cultures
這些物質文化的一個進入
Indeed a large number of these come in
確實大批的這些進來
In our Han settlements
在我們漢人的聚落裡面
where we meet the aborigines
在我們跟原住民接軌的地方
Industry in the Tang Department
唐部這堂的工業
Yes, earlier than Henan people have entered the southwestern coast of Taiwan, especially the wells in Tainan area,
對,比河南人更早的時間就已經進入到台灣西南海岸,尤其是台南地區的水井,
That is to say, water wells are not only used by Han people, we have so-called soil wells four thousand years ago,
這個也就是,水井並不是只有漢人才用水井,我們四千年前就有所謂的土井,
But knowing how to make it like this is definitely a technique that Han people have.
但是懂得這麼製作的,這個絕對是漢人才有的這種技術,
Bullock carts, Taiwan does not have cattle, Taiwan has cattle brought in from outside, as if I want to tell you, the number one dog in Taiwan that I did not talk about today,
牛車,台灣沒有牛,台灣有牛外面帶進來的,就好像我要跟各位講,我今天沒講的台灣的第一狗,
There are no dogs in Taiwan. Dogs in Taiwan are brought in by people.
台灣不會有狗,台灣有狗是人帶進來的,
This concept, everyone should know that only Han people have it.
這個概念,各位要知道,漢人才有的,
curtain
大幕
Ladies and gentlemen, we have seen the curtain five thousand years ago
各位,我們看到了五千年前的幕
The curtain of four thousand years ago, until now
四千年前的幕,一直到了
iron age right? yes
鐵器時代對不對?是
Is there such a pattern?
有沒有這麼樣子的格局
No, this is what Han people have
不會有,這個就是漢人才會有的
When will it happen? Han people will come in in large numbers
什麼時候才會有?漢人整個大批的進來
After bringing in one of his etiquette rules,
他的一個禮儀規範一起帶進來之後
they will have such a
他們才會有這樣子一個
This is solid evidence
這個是確確實實的證據
Do you believe in Buddhism?
有信佛教的吧
Whole Buddha Mother
整體佛母
inside our screen
在我們的幕障裡面
For this copper coin, he took his original
這個銅錢,他把他原來的
The lines on the pillars on the surface were worn away
這個表面的柱的那個紋是給磨掉了以後
Ko's
上面用柯的
Yes, this also explains
是,這個也是說明的
Taiwan
台灣
When will the mother of the whole Buddha, this branch, come?
整體佛母,這一個支派,什麼時候來?
Originally, they all thought that when Zheng Chenggong came in, what year was it?
原先他們都是認為是政成功進來的時間是哪一年
There is no high school, everyone is in the fourth grade and fifth grade, forget it
沒有高中的,大家這些都是四年級五年級的都忘記了
This, this, this, no, Mr. Xing, I will give you a copy later
這個,這個,這個,不是,行老師,你等一下還要給你一本
Yes, Hengran came in 1624
是,橫然人進來1624
Zheng Chenggong came in 1662,38 years
政成功進來1662,38年
However, such a time is different from what we now know about Qingkang in 1684.
可是,這樣子的一個時間,跟我們現在所知道的清康系1684年
caused by that time, even earlier
那時候所致的,還更早
This is all explained, how about it, the Han people came in
這個都是說明的,怎麼樣,漢人進來的
I was dumbfounded when I saw this one, once I was a child
看到這一個傻眼,我有一次到小時候
I'll talk about what's on my mind
我心事那邊去講
they see this
他們看到這一張
they say no
他們說不怪
Little ones love to scrape off
小來人愛刮掉
My Taiwanese is not correct
我的台語不準了
everyone is still laughing
大家還笑
The company came out because of the chairs in the company
社內因為社內椅子出來的
The thing about the chair coming out of the company
社內椅子出來的事
This is ironclad evidence
這個是鐵證
deer feet do it
鹿腳去做的
Deer's foot to carve out
鹿的腳去刻出來的
four different
四個不同的
Now scraping off is four, right?
現在刮掉就是四個嘛對不對
yes
是
China's earliest eighth to twelfth centuries
中國最早的八世紀到十二世紀
Dice of the eighth century
八世紀才有的這種骰子
good
好
Speaking of this
說到這邊
archeology
考古
actually tell you
實際上告訴各位的
Our ins and outs beyond ink
我們的來龍去墨之外
I often say
我經常說的
Archeology
學考古
nothing good actually
事實上沒有什麼好
But archeology is the experience of life
可是考古就是生活的體驗
I experience different chairs inside
我體驗不同的椅子裡面
the story of my life told
所告訴我的生活的故事
i got inside the archaeological chair
我到了考古椅子裡面
I go to learn other people's culture
我去學習別人的文化
no good or bad
沒有好或不好
no high or low
沒有高級或低級
you can say
你可以去說
This group of people fit in well or not
這群人適應的好或不好
Because every chair is like
因為每一個椅子都是怎麼樣
a group of people live there
一群人在那邊生活
live after a certain time
生活到某一個時間之後
they left
他們離開了
Whether the reason for leaving is good or bad
離開的原因到底是好或不好的
either positive or negative
或者是正面或者負面的
This is what we need from
這個都是要我們從
A pile of archaeological chairs inside
考古椅子裡面的一個堆積
come tell us
來告訴我們
But what I want to say about life and choices
可是我想說的生活跟抉擇
Time is changing this year, the environment is changing
今年來時間在變,環境在變
Many times borrowed from Tolstoy's
很多時候借用托爾斯泰的
Still borrowing from Tolstoy
還是借用托爾斯泰的
Once you leave the path you are used to
一旦離開了自己習慣的道路
we'll think we're lost
我們會以為自己迷了路
But what?
可是呢
we are under our feet
我們就在我們的腳下
A brand-new Kangzhuang Avenue is just about to open
嶄新的康莊大道才正要開啟
i hope after tonight
我希望今天晚上過後
you will think differently
你會有不同的思維
because we told you to
因為我們告訴你到
Taiwan's 5,000 Years
台灣的五千年
before this
在這之前
Sponsor Wales
Sponsor Wales
he is a biologist
他是一位生物學家
He made a vain complement to the genes of the whole world
他做了全世界的基因的徒補
what is his purpose
他的目的是什麼
he said
他說了
we must know our own interests
我們必須了解自己的利益
to fully realize who you are
才能够充分地认识自己是谁
Only then can we grasp the choice of where to go in the future
也才能够掌握未来要往哪里去的抉择
This is a little bit of what I have studied archeology over the years
这个是我这么多年来学习考古的一点点
Accumulate all one perception
累积所有的一个感悟
available to you
提供给各位
because
因为
Actually Taiwan is our home, right?
事实上台湾是我们的家,对不对
As a Taiwanese, one cannot understand Taiwanese culture
身为台湾人不能不懂台湾文化
Even with great wealth, the heart is empty
即便拥有在大的财富,心灵却是空虚的
Nanke Medical Subgroup, Archaeological Research on Archaeological Medical Subgroup
南科医子群,考古医子群的考古研究
It is to provide us with an understanding of Taiwan's five thousand years of culture
是提供我们来理解台湾五千年来的文化
a platform for history
历史的一个平台
Why?
为什么?
The foreground is in the National History Outline
前幕在国史大纲里面
Give us another way of thinking
提供给我们另外一种思维
Foreign nationals should have a little knowledge of their own history
異國國民對本國歷史應該略有所知
You Bi's Warmth and Tranquility to History
尤必對歷史之溫情與靜義
No extreme nihilism
不可抱一偏激的虛無主義
When believing that foreign nationals can meet the above-mentioned conditions
當信異國國民如果能夠具備上述的這些條件的時候
Taiwan has a future
台灣才有未來
This is a little thought I want to offer you
這個是我想提供給各位的一點思考
thank you
謝謝各位
Thanks
謝謝
very well said
講得很精彩
Talking about a thousand years is like talking about small things
講一千年好像要講一些小事情一樣
one afternoon before a family thing
一下午前一家事情
Third sister
三姐
I want to do a little more questions
我想再做一點很多問題
Ask their two keynote speakers and filmmakers
請教他們兩位主講人跟影言人
is it starting now
現在是不是就開始了
come on now start here
來 現在從這邊開始
ask Dr. Lee
請問李博士
When did the name Taiwan start to be taken? Who took the name Taiwan?
台灣這個名字是什麼時候開始取這個台灣這個名字是誰取的
I'll give it to you first, don't ask me
先給你啦,你不要問我啦
Dry warm, really
幹溫喔,真的是喔
When was Taiwan called Taiwan?
台灣什麼時候叫台灣的
Taiwan this
台灣這
Taiwan from a Historical Perspective
從歷史的角度來看台灣
Or do you want to look at the name Taiwan
還是你要看台灣這個名字
The name Taiwan is actually
台灣這個名字實際上
very late
很晚的時候
Taiwan does not know me
台灣並不是知我
Not the whole island, where is Taiwan
不是全島,台灣是在哪裡
Tainan, yes
台南啊,是啊
when was taiwan borrowed
台灣什麼時候才被借用
to cover the whole of Taiwan
來變成涵蓋的整個台灣的
This is what we all have to think about
這個就是我們大家要思考的
This is one for all of us to think about
這個是我們大家要思考的一個
Taiwan is not called Taiwan
台灣也不叫台灣
Dayuan
叫大園啊
Also called burying the injustice
還叫做埋冤喔
Taiwan
台灣喔
What are you talking about?
都在聊聊啊 都在什麼?
Taiwan is guilty
台灣埋冤啊
yes i just tell you this
是 我只告訴你這些
The rest you go to Google
剩下的你去找Google
yes
是
Now that we are doing it, everyone wants to study Taiwan
現在在做了 有人都要研究台灣
Experts from this research bureau in Taiwan
台灣這個研究局的專家
I saw the news in the newspaper not long ago
我是不久前報上看到有新聞
I want you to give me an answer
我想 希望你們給我點個答案
That is to say, at that time, there were reports in the newspaper that in Indonesia
就是說那時候報上有報導說在印度尼西亞
found one very well there
發現一個很排在那
row there
排在那
That is to say, about one meter
就是說大概一公尺左右
that dampens the hobbit
那減震著哈比人
then i was thinking
那我在想到
That is to say, our Lin Zhuyin has a machine called platooning machine.
就是說我們那個林柱銀有個叫做排人機
That is, Lin Zhuyin has a series called platooning machine
就是林柱銀有個系列叫做排人機
That means he is a platoon machine
那表示說他這個排人機
Maybe it means he tracked down the assembly
可能就是說他追測到組裝
and is a
而且是一種
or at least touched
或者至少有碰過
Such a rowdy person
這種很排的人
I don't know if it's the element
我不知道是不是這個元素品
with this
跟這個
You say indonesia they hobbies won what's the relationship
你說印度尼西亞他們Hobbies贏了什麼關係
very good
很好
Hahaha
哈哈哈
Because I brought several copies today
因為我今天帶了好幾本
Can't go home yet
還沒有送完不能回家
So I'll give you that first
所以說那個趕快先給你
The Poet of the Fowles
那個叫福爾人詩人
not that
不是那個
The real Hobbies because he was made into a movie
真正Hobbies人是因為把他拍成電影
That's why I call him Hobbies
才叫他Hobbies人
OK
OK
good
好
It was actually different in those days
那時代上面事實上不一樣
The Hobbies should now be the Fowl poet
Hobbies人現在應該那個福爾人詩人
The Dating I have now
現在有的那個Dating
The current date seems to be more than 40,000 years.
現在有的那個定年好像是四萬多年吧
Zhang Xian
張憲
even earlier
還更早
So this is what we call these
所以呢這個跟我們所謂的這些
The so-called short blacks are all together
所謂的矮黑人大家一起都在
talk
談
I
我
I will tell you an experience
我跟各位講一個經驗
once
有一次
that is
就是
Because at that time it seemed that
因為那時候好像是那個
That female Vice President Li Xiulian?
那位李秀蓮女副總統吧
So when I'm sure
所以我在肯定的時候
That's exactly what he posted
那正好他就發布了什麼樣子的
sea ​​black person's question
海黑人的那個問題
The one at the pit management in Hengchun
那這個恆春的那個坑管處的
Liao's Liao's
就說廖氏廖氏
Are there any sea blacks here?
我們這邊到底有沒有海黑人
speak faster faster
的話更快的更快的講一下
That's hard to do
那個好不容易可以
Change to the opportunity to go online
改到機會可以上網
This is called reporting
這個叫上報嘛
can you make a name
可以出個名嘛
this is one
這個就是一個
I can't find any evidence so far
目前找不到任何的證據
we say this
我們這樣子說
you want to talk about sea black
你要講說海黑人
only one meter
只有一公尺的嘛
at least we have to say
至少我們要講是說
is he a child
他到底是小孩子
Are you still an adult?
還是是成年熟年的人嘛
right
對不對
But this figure actually has his range
可是這個身材事實上有他的一個範圍
But the real so-called dwarfs
不過真正所謂的這些矮黑人
So far there is no such substantive evidence in Taiwan
到目前為止在臺灣沒有這些實質的證據
Then you say this dwarf skill
那你說這個矮靈技
Does it have anything to do with these dwarfs?
到底跟這些矮黑人有沒有關係
We said that there are short blacks in the Philippines
我們講矮黑人在菲律賓是有的
Wait a minute, maybe Mr. Zhang
這個等一下或許讓張先生
Mr. Zhang did this archaeology in the Philippines
張先生在菲律賓做過這個考古的
they have actual evidence of this
他們有實際的這個證據
So far, there is no such evidence in Taiwan
那到目前為止臺灣還沒有這樣子的證據
OK
好不好
I think this question is actually pretty good.
我想這個問題其實蠻好的
Because dwarfs actually have dwarf skills
因為矮黑人其實我們就有矮靈技
I think that Academician Li just now
我想在座剛那個李院士
Where is Academician Li Renguo?
李任國李院士在哪邊
He has written articles
他專門寫過文章
Talking about the short black people in Taiwan
談臺灣的矮黑人
But mainly from the legend
但是主要從傳說裡面
There are many tribes with legends about dwarfs
有很多的部落都有矮黑人的傳說
Are there any dwarfs?
到底有沒有矮黑人
In fact, in the past
過去其實
Someone recently told me
最近還有一個人給我講
I don't know if it's true or not
我不曉得真的假的
He said I'll tell you a secret
他說我告訴你一個秘密喔
He said there is a place to keep secret now
他說現在有個地方保密喔
Also punish the short black man like this
也罰起來矮黑人這樣子
I said where is it?
那我說在哪裡啊
He won't talk
他就不講啊
don't speak
不講
But I can tell you
不過我可以給各位講
Now there are some clues
這個現在是有一些端倪
clue
端倪
What about the little black man?
那麼這個矮黑人呢
In fact, in Southeast Asia
其實在東南亞
is the branch of Malaysia
就是分部的馬來西亞
the Philippines
菲律賓
The three should be universal
分部的三當普遍
that this
那這個
Do you have this in Taiwan?
台灣的這個有沒有
Then recently we were
那麼最近我們在
Eight Immortals Cave
八仙洞
It is the ruins of the Eight Immortals Cave in Taitung
就是台東的八仙洞遺址
layer we found
我們發現的一層
About 5,000 to 6,000 years ago
大概在五千到六千年前
this level of culture
這一層文化
So the Nagahama culture that Han just talked about
那麼漢剛剛講的長濱文化
The one tens of thousands of years earlier
更早的幾萬年的那個
there is one in the middle
中間有一個
There is an interval in the middle of more than 10,000 years
差了一萬多年的中間一個間隔
what about these things
那麼這些東西呢
it is also
它同樣的是
very simple times
非常簡單的時期
so very this this
那麼非常的這個這個
nor any naughtiness
也沒有任何的淘氣
Nor is there any such sign of agriculture
也沒有任何農業的這種跡象
but we think
但是我們認為
it does have
它的確是有
people on this level exist
這層的人存在
Is it possible that this layer of people is a short black man?
那這層人有沒有可能是矮黑人
So far we haven't found any human bones
到現在我們沒有挖到任何的人骨
But from his cultural layer exists
但是從他的文化層存在
The world of five or six thousand years looks like
五六千年界看起來
and his periods are very similar to those of the Filipinos
以及他的時期和菲律賓人這些時期非常類似
So we can only speculate
所以我們只能夠推測
he may be a dwarf
他可能是矮黑人
what about this part
那在這個部分呢
We hope that in the future there will be more and more evidence
我們希望將來會越來越多的證據
In fact, archeology is to slowly test
其實考古學就是慢慢要考
Accumulation of data bit by bit
一點一地的資料的累積
Well, now there are some clues
那麼現在已經慢慢有一些端倪了
I believe that in the future this matter may
我相信將來這個事情可能會
There must be a way to make it clear one day
一定會有辦法可以水落石出的一天
i think this is there
我想這個是有的
So as for the Flourish just now
那麼剛剛至於談到那個Flourish
It's this Hobby stuff
就是這個Hobby這些東西
Well, there are many different theories in this past
那麼這個過去有很多不同的學說
Some people think this may be modern man
有人認為這個可能是現代人
he's just sick
他只是一種病態
so he is short
所以他的身材很矮
about one meter high
大概一米高
Then the capacity is about 350 cm
然後那容量大概350這個CM
Just 350CC
就350CC
Now our people are 1300CC
現在我們的人是1300CC
Of course people now
當然現在的人
Then they only have 350CC
那他們只有350CC
Why are there such small people?
為什麼會有這麼小的人呢
So many people thought it was a kind of modern man
所以當初很多人認為是一種現代人
because he is very late
因為他年代很晚
just ten thousand years
就一萬多年
is sick
是個病態
But recent new research
但是最近新的研究
Already pushed back the age
已經把這個年代推早了
think he is not modern
認為他不是現代人
he may be an older
他可能是一個更古老的
Homo erectus
就叫直立人
only in Southeast Asia
只是在東南亞地區
gradually affected by the environment
慢慢的收到環境的影響
after isolation
孤立起來之後
Will stay on this Flourish island
會留在這個Flourish島上面
So the problem is not solved yet
所以這個問題其實還沒有解決
There are still a lot of political discussions
現在目前都還在很多的政論
But it's always getting brighter
但是總是會越變越明
Now more and more evidence
現在越來越多的證據
Including a mathematical genetic evidence
包括一算學的基因的證據
Evidence that includes these cultural medicines
包括這些文化醫療的證據
Wait so we can learn more about it
等等可以讓我們去越來越了解它
So this so-called Flourish Men
所以這個所謂這個Flourish Men
what is going on
到底是怎麼回事
welcome
歡迎
Thanks
謝謝
Come
來
we are grateful
我們很感謝
Okay, thank you
好 謝謝
Thanks
謝謝
I am very grateful to Huang Mu Yuanchang this time
很感謝這次的黃沐遠長
give me a chance to welcome
給我歡迎機會
I am a researcher at the Central Domestic Research Institute
我是中央國內所研究員
Hong Deqian
洪德謙
First of all, I would also like to thank Zhang Yanshi and Teacher Li
首先也感謝張彥施跟李老師
so wonderful
這麼精彩的
It's also very humorous, so the whole process will be very lively
也很幽默 所以整個過程會很活潑
I personally also thank a lot
我個人也謝謝很多
Then I raised my hand mainly to see if I could get Mr. Liao
然後我舉手主要也是看能不能得到廖師
go home
回家好了
a little scared
有一點嚇
Then I just tell a little story
然後我個人就是講一點小故事
I went to Willingdon, New Zealand in 1999 to attend a conference
我1999年到紐西蘭的威林登的委託里亞大學去開會了
Then from the airport to the hotel where you leave
然後從機場到住的離館
just hitchhike
就搭切人車
Then cut the car driver to look like the name of the show
然後切人車司機看起來就像演出名貓膩
He also looked at me
他也看了我機業
then suddenly asked me
然後突然問我
It seems that our competition is spiritually a little painful
好像我們比賽心有靈性一點痛
He asked me if you are from Taiwan
他問我說你是不是來自台灣
I said yes
我說對啊
He said that our ancestors
他說這樣我們祖先
seems to have a common ancestor
好像是有共同祖先
He said they have a heart
他說他們有心
Since, as in 1999,
既然正如在1999年的時候
that is to say at that time
就是說那時候
Formal recognition of Māori ancestry may have come from Taiwan
正式承認毛利人祖先可能來自台灣
So I just answer him
所以我就跟他回答一句
say we are brothers
說我們是兄弟
So let me feel at ease even when I'm bullying others
所以讓我就是大欺人之外也覺得放心
because abroad
因為在國外
First time to New Zealand
第一次到紐西蘭去
then i was curious
然後那時候我就很好奇
So three or four thousand years ago
所以這樣在三四千年前
How can there be a way to cross the ocean from Taiwan
怎麼有辦法從台灣漂洋過海
as far as new zealand
到紐西蘭這麼遠的地方
Then wait until I visit their Rijksmuseum
然後等到我參觀他們的國立博物館
large-scale visitor
採訪的大物
because he has two canoes
因為他擺著兩艘獨木舟
That canoe has planks in the middle
那獨木舟中間有木板
And there are bamboo poles at the front and back to tie it up
還有前後有那個竹竿把它綁住了
So in the middle it can be
所以中間它還可以就是
Can be horizontal
可以橫度
That is to say, traffic is also possible
就是說也可以交通
because of this
因為這樣
Only in this way is there a way to save the coolness
用這樣的方式才有辦法橫度大涼
So I feel very cooperative
所以我就覺得非常配合
also very active
也非常肯動
Taiwan's coastal people crossed the sea beautifully so early
台灣的這個沿著民這麼早就漂亮過海
Then in Australia there is a kind of tango
然後在澳洲有一種叫淡丁果
I heard that it is also native to Taiwan.
聽說也是台灣的土果
their present archaeological DNA finds
他們現在的考古的DNA發現
It may have passed through Australia and then chased to Newia
可能有經過澳洲再追到紐西亞
So many people in Newia like to translate
所以紐西亞很多人喜歡譯
This is very similar to the Yan Zhuwen in Taiwan
這個是跟台灣的言註文是非常相像
so i have a suggestion
所以我有一個建議
That is to say, Newcia itself is kinder
就是說紐西亞本身比較友善
He has a good reservation about Maori culture and chairs
他對毛利人的文化還有椅子保留非常好
So our Zhuang Yan also has forty-one poems
所以我們那個莊燕也有四十一首
should put this like this blue co chair
應該要把這個像這個藍柯椅子
Because this Lan Ke chair is more than ten years old
因為這個藍柯椅子是十幾年代
Is a national security officer of Taiwan
是一個台灣的國保
Good things should be shared with this country
好東西應該要跟這個難道與其國家要分享
Therefore, cooperation should be strengthened
所以應該要加強合作
Matsu
就是馬祖
Taiwan Matsu should be present
台灣馬祖應該要出席
Thank you for the above
以上 以上兼理 謝謝
Thanks
謝謝
thanks for your question
謝謝你的問題
but i tell you
不過我告訴你
i have the same experience
我有同樣的經歷
I am here
我在
I forgot what year it is now
我現在忘了哪一年了
There is a man named Force Leach
有一位叫做Force Leach
He specializes in fish
他專門研究魚的
he told me
他告訴我
He said the profiteers were probably from your Amis
他說牟利人很可能就是來自於你們的阿美族
good
好
I don't care
那我先不管
I said I don't know
我說我不知道
but he came to me
可是他來找我
He especially ran to Taiwan
他特別跑到台灣來
because he went to hawaii
是因為他到夏威夷去
I heard I have a lot of fish in my hand
聽說我手上有很多的魚
what fish
有什麼魚
variety of these fish
各種不同的這些魚
Especially the ghost knife
特別是叫鬼頭刀的
Because he thought there was a group of people chasing ghost swords
因為他就認為有一群追著鬼頭刀的人
from Taiwan all the way to New Zealand
就是從台灣一直追到紐西蘭
You believe it or you don't believe it
你相信也好 你不相信也好
Believers, Hengxin, but I want to tell you
信者恆信 可是我要告訴各位
Peter Biaogu he thinks so too
Peter 標固 他也這麼認為
He said that this group of people went out five thousand years ago
他說五千年前就是這一群人往外走
chasing ghost knife
追著鬼頭刀
I said you also want to eat fish, are you eating fish?
我說你也要吃魚 你有在吃魚
where did ghost head knife come from
鬼頭刀是從哪裡來的
Do you know this biological chain?
各位知不知道這個生物鏈
Do you know this flying fish medicine?
各位知不知道這個飛魚劑
When does flying fish medicine start
飛魚劑什麼時候開始
The ghost knife came after the flying fish
鬼頭刀追著飛魚來的
so i am
所以我在
And Lambi what will I see?
而蘭比我看到的會是什麼?
The ghost head knife that started with the useless fish is here
廢魚開始的鬼頭刀就來了
Ghost head knife is here
鬼頭刀來了
what came from
什麼來的?
fish name
魚名
what fish name
什麼魚名?
please give me this room
請開本房給我
I'll give you one
我一本給你一本
your jokes are funny
你講的笑話很好笑
let everyone have a copy
讓大家捏有一本
After the ghost head knife comes, it will be a fin fish
鬼頭刀來了以後再來就是鰭魚啦
fin fish
鰭魚啊
Hengchun's most famous
恆春最有名的叫做
Broken Fish Umbrella
破魚傘啦
This is a biological store
這個就是一個生物店
good
好
But what is this?
可是這個是什麼來?
go from south to north
從南邊往北邊走
Who is coming to the south?
什麼人才往南邊來?
everytime i talk to japanese
我每一次我跟日本的
my very good
我那個非常要好的
he passed away last year
他去年已經過世了
everytime i go to japan
我每一次我到日本去的時候
i will
我就會
what would i bring mullet roe for him
我會帶什麼?帶烏魚子給他啦
mullet roe
烏魚子啦
Mullet roe, everyone knows mullet roe
烏魚子各位知道烏魚子
Mullet roe, especially men like to eat it
烏魚子那個尤其是男性特別喜歡吃
But it's better not to eat
可是最好不要吃
Vice President Wang, you must not eat
王副院長你一定不能吃
good
好
when will the mullet come
烏魚什麼時候才來
everyone is right
大家對啦
Everyone has an idea, right?
大家有概念了對不對
what was it like when you were young
年輕人的時候才怎麼樣
The mullet will come
烏魚就跑到來
The mullet will grow soft only in Taiwan
烏魚要到台灣才會長軟
That's why there are so many mullet roe in Taiwan
所以台灣才會有那麼多的烏魚子
what is this?
這個是什麼?
gift from god
上帝給的禮物
yes
是
So this is what I'm trying to say
所以這個就是我就是想說
How did the coming and going of the crowd happen?
人群的來來往往到底是怎麼一個發生的
In fact, here in Taiwan
事實上台灣這裡
I will also tell you
我還會跟各位講
I just returned
我剛剛還
I have no special instructions for you
沒有特別的跟各位指講
5000, 4000, 3000, 2000
5000年、4000年、3000年、2000年
These people who live in these Nanke Park in Tainan
住在這些台南南科園區的這些人
not the continuation of their lives
並不是他們的生命的延續
not a continuation of biological life
不是生物生命的延續
Can you understand this sentence
各位聽得懂這一句
Each varies between 5,000 and 4,000 years
每一個不同5000年到4000年中間
this group of people left
是這群人走了
Like the one we saw 7 meters down
像我們看到的7公尺下面的那一
it just broke
它就斷掉了
it's gone
它就沒了
Another place for another 4,000 years
另外4000年來的另外一個地方
Its chair is called Youxianfang Chair
它的那個椅子叫幼仙方椅子
You Xianfang chair we saw
幼仙方椅子我們看到了
4000 years ago
有4000年前的
2000 years ago
有2000年前的
not 3000 years ago
沒有3000年前的
what is explained here
這裡面說明的是什麼
Humans choose the one above the living environment
人類選擇居住環境上面的一個
Commonality
共通性
Three thousand years ago, it was the one with the highest distribution density in the entire Nanke Park
三千年前是整個南科園區裡面分布密度最高的一個
Where did this group of people come from? Actually we are still chasing
這群人從哪裡來?實際上我們都還在追
This is what I have been doing with Mr. Zhang for so many years.
這個也是這麼多年來跟著張先生在做
He let me have a lot of space for these studies
他讓我有非常多的這些學習的空間
The ecological legacy of our material culture from mischievous, stony assortments
我們從淘氣、石氣各式各樣的這些物質文化的生態遺留的
What we want to chase is no matter where he comes from
我們想要追的是不管他從哪裡來
But when he lived in this place
可是他生活在這一塊地方的時候
How do they adapt to this environment
他們怎麼樣子來適應這個環境
This is what we really want to pursue
這個才是我們真正想要去追的
live here live well or not
活在這邊活得好或不好
i want to tell you
我想跟各位講
If what Golanby over there told me was
如果鵝蘭比那邊告訴我的是
More than 85% of the time when eating the same type of shellfish
85%以上都是吃同樣一種貝類的時候
good or bad
好或不好
definitely not good
絕對不好
right
對不對
This is what I was able to from the archaeological site
這個就是我從考古遺址能夠
Being able to discover how it behaves on a strategy that keeps them sustainable
能夠發現到怎麼樣子在讓他們永續經營的一個策略上面的一個表現
Yeah, that's what I've been wanting to share with you all.
是 這個才是我一直想要跟各位分享的
We chased from inside the archaeological site to the end guys.
我們從考古遺址裡面去追 追到最後各位
If you just want to chase who it is
你如果只是想要追 它是什麼人 你是什麼人 它是什麼人
One day I got a copy, it seems my wife gave it to me
有一天 我有一份 好像是我太太給我的吧
的DNA
的DNA
A test of DNA Now the technology of DNA testing, you can know it by spitting
DNA的一個測試 現在測DNA的技術 你吐一口口水就可以知道
how many kinds of people do you have
你有多少種 什麼樣子的人 什麼樣子的人 什麼樣子的人
Turns out their first test was
結果他們第一次的測試是
The French must scold the Germans to death, they are so dirty, or something, between each other's workshops, but after a week, they found out that they were still Cutten and the Brothers.
法國人一定罵死德國人,好髒,或者是怎樣的,彼此之間的工間,結果一個禮拜以後發現,彼此之間還是Cutten and the Brothers。
In my age, Shi Xiaorong, do you know? Shi Xiaorong, when we met on the high-speed rail once, you come to study who I am?
在我的年紀裡面,施孝榮,各位知道嗎?施孝榮,有一次我們在高鐵見面的時候,你來研究我到底是什麼人?
He himself told me that 1/16 of me is Han Chinese, and I am indeed, you can ask him.
他自己就跟我講我有16分之1是漢人,我這個是確確實實,你們可以去問他。
He said so and so and so and so, how.
他說誰誰誰誰誰,怎麼樣。
So who am I to say that you are? I am patriarchal. Who are the people left in your agreement? It doesn't matter, if you live here, you agree with this place, you agree with this place.
那到底我說那你是什麼人?我排灣族德啊。你的協議裡面留的到底是什麼人?不重要,你如果住在這邊,你認同這個地方,認同這個地方。
Agree with this place, this is the attitude that matters
認同這個地方,這是態度才重要
This is what I want to share with you
這個才是我想要跟各位去分享的
still come, sorry
還是來,對不起
there are people
還有人
i want to ask
我想請問一下
Ask Professor Li
請教李教授
just inside the archaeological sawdust
剛剛在考古的木屑裡面
A few of them are thorn slices or peach slices
有幾個鋪的那個是刺片還是桃片
That's the blade
那是就刀片
what culture is that
那是什麼文化
Niaosong culture
鳥松文化
bird pine iron
鳥松鐵器的
That's the pavement and that's
那是鋪片跟那個是
not tile
不是鋪片
Lay out
就鋪片
Slab
鋪片
tile or
鋪片還是
Is it paving or
是鋪片還是
Slab
鋪片
I can't see clearly
我看不清楚
is a tile
是鋪片
what does that do
那有什麼作用
like a floor covering
就好像是一個地板鋪面一樣
what is it like in culture
它是什麼樣子的文化
Niaosong culture as we know it now
我們現在認知的鳥松文化
I said where did it come from, right?
我說從哪裡來的對不對
Haruya
哇哉
Ha ha ha ha
哈哈哈哈
You say that culture is from
你說那個文化是從
that culture
那個那個文化
That culture at that time was the Niaosong culture
那個文化那個年代是鳥鬆文化
iron age bird pine
是鐵器時代的鳥鬆
The second question to ask you
第二個問題請教你的
Dr. Lee, you just said that you are 1/16 Taiwanese
那個李博士你剛說你有16分之1的台灣人
Nah
不是啦
Shi Xialong
石下龍
Teacher, you didn't listen to what you said
老師你講你都沒聽啊
Then what is your 15/16?
那請問你的16分之15是
I'm not me
我不是我啦
It's Shixialong
是石下龍啦
Shi Xialong
石下龍
Shi Xialong sings famous songs
石下龍一個唱名歌的啦
sing a famous song
唱名歌的啦
Taiwanese physical education teacher
台灣族的體育老師
He is a physical education teacher at the Normal University
他是師大的體育老師
1 in 16 Taiwanese
16分之1的台灣人
1 out of 16 Koreans
那16分之1的韓人啦
No la
沒有啦
he means to say
他的意思就是說
He's in one of his syndicates
他在他的一個協同裡面
There are different
有不同的
as if i'm going to tell you guys
就好像我要告訴各位的
I am 2006 07
我2006年07年
Go to America this year, go to Four Brite in America
今年到美國去,到美國去Four Brite
In our office there is a sister who is tall and burly
我們辦公室裡面有一個人高馬大的一個妹妹
bright girl
亮妹啊
After I finished speaking, he said I have Shuffle Shape
我講完了以後他說我有Shuffle Shape
That is, there is a model behind your front teeth
就是你的門齒後面是有一個機型
We call it model incisors
我們叫做機型門齒
What is a model incisor?
機型門齒是什麼?
Model incisors are a feature of Mongolia
機型門齒是蒙古總的一個特徵
Everyone, you will definitely look in the mirror when you go back.
各位你們回去一定會去照鏡子
There will be model incisors
就是會有機型門齒
This Mr. Zhang even wrote the article on the front teeth of the model
這個張先生都還寫過機型門齒的那個文章
good
好
He is from Central and South America
他中南美來的
He said I have it too
他就說我也有啊
he has too
他也有啊
Model incisors
機型門齒啊
Then I said how could you have
結果我說你怎麼會有
I go out mother Japanese
我外出母日本人啊
yes
是啊
so this is
所以這個就是
We are in every human biological life
我們在每一個人的生物生命裡面
you probably are
你很可能你在
Because your genes are likely to be in a certain person
因為你的基因很可能碰上的是屬於某一個人
But how come you don't matter
可是你怎麼會這個不重要
i still turn around
我還是回過頭來
it doesn't matter what kind of person you are
你是什麼種人都不重要
When you live in Taiwan and you identify with Taiwan
你如果住在台灣你就認同台灣的時候
this is important
這個才重要
OK
好不好
Thanks
謝謝
Excuse me
請問一下
your article first
你的文章先
your question first
你的問題先
you have a lot of questions
你問題很多
your speech was wonderful
你演講很精彩
I am a foreigner
我是用外人士
i want to ask a question
我想請教一個問題
It's because you just broke a bag
就是你剛才有一個包破
That is to say, there are many points made of carbon stone mountains
就是說有很多點用碳石山做的
Is it all your carbon car
是不是所有的你的碳車
the point of the chair
就是椅子的點
Then do the carbon stone mountain one
然後做碳石山的那個
A point that is not a chair is a chair
不是椅子的點是一個椅子
the back shell of a chair
一個椅子裡面的背殼
the sample taken
所抽取的樣本
the one to do
去做的那個
Let's talk about the development of the same number
我們講說同位數的養成
that that
那那個
because you said five thousand years
因為你說五千年
I think it used to be
我看以前那個就是
It's like carbon dating
好像用碳實實做定年
I don't know the degree of certainty of your year
不曉得你這個年份的這個確定的程度
Is it possible to use carbon to do it?
是不是有用碳實實去做
that is to say you
就是說你
yes yes
有有有
This has
這個有
This we send a different lab
這個我們送不同的這個lab
We send to different labs
我們送不同的實驗室
with beta
有beta的
also send beta
也送beta的
now present
現在目前
National Taiwan University has a linear accelerator
台大有有有直線加速器
before him
在他之前
We also use the traditional
我們也用傳統的
Liu Songgui's Teacher Liu helped us make it
劉松貴的劉老師幫我們做的
So what was done five thousand years ago
所以現在所做的這些五千年前
is actually more specific
就是事實上比較具體的
We are now four thousand two to four thousand eight
我們現在是四千二到四千八
four thousand two to four thousand eight
四千二到四千八
we are just
我們只是是
Humblendon's take it five thousand years
Humblendon的把它當作五千年
OK
好不好
general anthropology and archeology
那個一般人類學跟考古學
They are worried that in this era of colonial
他們就擔心會被那個在colonial的這個時代
used by imperialism
都是被帝國主義運用
That is to say, have you ever considered this problem?
那就是說假的你有沒有顧慮到這個問題
That is to say, will it be possible?
就是說會不會可能就是說
It's just like this, that's colonial
就是跟這個就是說colonial的
This amperiorism this relationship
這個amperiorism這個關係
This is the right and wrong place of the position
這個是立場的是非之地
i want to tell you
我要跟各位講
I used to talk to Xu Zhongwen and Teacher Xu
我曾經跟許中文與許老師
Everyone knows Xu Zhongwen and Mr. Xu
各位知道許中文與許老師
I had a talk with him
我跟他談過一個
I said I privately
我說我私底下
Now record it and turn it off
現在錄音先把它關起來好了
I said
我說
Taiwan is a pirate economy
台灣都是海盜式經濟
pirate economy
海盜式經濟
Surely economists disagree with me
一定經濟學家不同意我這麼說法
Pirate economy is
海盜式經濟就是
be more transparent
說得比較透明一點
that is
就是說
I'm here, I'll leave after I'm done catching
我來到這邊,抓完了我就走人了
Nobody thinks of this place as the place where I'm going to live here for generations
沒有人把這個地方去當作我世世代代要在這邊生活的地方
I just told him I said
我就跟他講我說
Hey, Nanke has been here for 5,000 years and left, and the one for 4,000 years has come and left
哎,南科五千年來了,走人了,四千年的來了,走人了
We all regard this group of people as the first inhabitants of Taiwan
這群人我們都當他是台灣的先住民
But are these people from the same group?
可是這些人到底是不是同一群人進來的
i tell you privately
我私底下告訴你
yes, they are all passers-by
是,都是過客
Excuse me, if you want the woman of 5,000 years, you will come here after 4,000 years
請問要那五千年的女人,你後來就走四千年的來了
Have they tested you for BNO?
他們對你們做過BNO的檢測嗎?
No
沒有
I'm sorry, we are now talking about Mr. Zhang
對不起,我們現在張先生說的
we did it but it ain't out yet
我們做了,可是還沒有出來
or we can't do it
或者是我們做不出來
Don't get me wrong, it's not that we can't do it
這個不要誤會,不是我們做不出來
yes we can't do it
是,我們做不出來
We have done a lot, just to test
我們做了很多出來,就是去試驗
We also sent these specimens to Germany
我們這些標本還送到德國
called MACPRAC
叫做MACPRAC
The best organization in the world to make this DNA
全世界做這個DNA最好的機構
We put the mark down, it can't make it
我們把標重去,它做不出來
Why? Not its experimental parallax
為什麼呢?並不是它的實驗視差
because it is a top
因為它是一個頂級的
Because our preservation environment in Taiwan is too poor
因為是我們的台灣保存環境太差
Because of the DNA that exists in that bone
因為那個骨頭裡的所存在的這個DNA的這些
these things are gone
這些東西都沒有了
So it can't be pulled out, so it can't be made
所以它抽不出來,所以就做不出來
Then this, if the storage environment is good, there is no problem
那麼這個,如果保存環境好,都沒有問題
Like we were recently, our colleagues are on Liang Island in Matsu
像我們最近在,我們同仁在馬祖的亮島
Look at him for eight thousand years
你看他八千年呢
He also sent the laboratory
他同樣送了實驗室
He can do it inside
他裡面就做得出來
Because of the quantity-guided human stock?
因為那個量導的人股呢
It's inside this shell
是放在這個貝殼裡面
So shells have a natural
所以貝殼它有一種天然的
can be a function of preservation
可以一種保存的一種作用
Because it's all that stuffy stuff
因為它都是那種蓋質的東西
So it can also save
所以它裡面還可以保存
its these
它的這些
These can be done with DNA
這些可以做的DNA的
these things come out
這些東西出來
But our Nanke stuff
但是我們南科的東西
did much
做了很多
In Taiwan, we also do Taiwan Majie Hospital
在台灣我們也做台灣馬街醫院
Then send it to Bucks Plank in Germany
然後送到這個德國的Bucks Plank
can't do it
都做不出來
now there is a hope
現在有一個希望
we send to ireland
我們送到愛爾蘭
a lab in ireland
愛爾蘭的一個實驗室
It is specialized in ear bones
它是專門做耳骨
the bone inside the ear
耳裡面的耳朵裡面的骨頭的
Then this bone is wrapped in the head
那這個骨頭是在頭裡包的
maybe it will be better
說不定會好一點
and won't
而且不會
Will not be affected by the outside environment
不會外面受到外面的環境影響
So now we have a batch of specimens
所以現在我們一批標本
currently doing
目前正在做
We hope to get a result
我們希望可以出來一個結果
maybe there is one
說不定有一個
amazing discovery
令人驚奇的發現
don't seem to know
好像不曉得
the last one
最後這一位
then this one
然後這一位
two more questions
還有兩位問題
please teach me
請教一下
Teeth are very important to our life
這個牙齒對我們人的生活是很重要的
If we're missing teeth, find a way to get implants, right?
如果我們缺牙,想辦法去植牙對不對
Why did Yan Zhiwenming pull out his teeth?
那顏治文明為什麼會去把牙齒拔掉
what do they mean
他們代表什麼意義
or why do they think this way
還是他們為什麼這種想法
He seems to have pulled out the left and right teeth of the front teeth
他好像是把大門牙的左右兩邊那個牙齒拔掉
Why is there such absorption
為什麼會有這種吸收
Please advise, thank you
請指教,謝謝
Thank you, this is because I still have two copies, hurry up and get one copy for each person
謝謝,這個因為我還有兩本,趕快一個人一本
this heavy
這個重
I want to know more about Nanke
我想多了解一下南科的
It's okay, you come with me
沒關係,你跟我來
That tooth extraction is, this is what we are talking about
那個拔牙是,這個就是我們講說
A Cultural Trait of the Someshima Uzu
染島宇族的一個文化特徵
According to our current understanding
根據我們現在所的一個理解
it's a symbol of a rite of passage
它是一個成年禮的一個象徵
But in our cognition of five thousand years ago
可是在我們五千年以來的這樣子的一個認知裡面
Five thousand years ago, both men and women
五千年前男女都有
But to compare
可是到比較
Let's say most of this Iron Age happens only to women
比方說這個鐵器時代的大部分都只發生在女性
And women we see now are called mature years
而且女性我們現在所看到的叫做熟年
That is to say, it will be at least 16 years old
就是說至少會是16歲以後
Occurs after age 16
16歲以後才會發生
Let's talk about the size they drew. It is the side door size and the full size.
他們拔的尺寸我們講說尺寸它是側門尺跟全尺
And only pull the top but not the bottom
而且只拔上面不拔下面
This is a cultural characteristic of the Yu people in South Island
這個就是一個南島宇族的一個文化特徵
Thanks
謝謝
Thank you two teachers for their wonderful speeches
謝謝兩位老師非常精彩的演講
What I want to ask is that there are a lot of naughty people in today's information
我想請教的是今天的資料裡面有看到很多的淘氣
They do these naughty things to say that everyone can almost do it
他們做這些淘氣是說大家都差不多差不多會做
Or is it that they have a dedicated group of people who keep the technique of being naughty?
還是說他們就是有專門一群人保存做淘氣的技術
then maybe better
然後可能越做越好
Then even do trade or say there is actually no
然後甚至做貿易還是說其實沒有
Naka didn't mention this
那卡就沒有提到這一點
so i'm pretty good
所以我相當好
Thanks
謝謝
That's a great question we've also done
這個很好的問題我們也做過
With Mr. Chen Wenshan, we have worked together from five thousand years, four thousand years, three thousand years
跟陳文山老師我們一起做過的從五千年、四千年、三千年
Different from the analysis of these components above
不同的一個這些成分的分析上面
We especially do the so-called speech
我們特別去做言相所謂的言相
It is a component of a stone in a river in your place
就是你地方的一個河川裡面的一個石頭的一個成分
Let's understand if it's local
我們去理解會不會是在地的
Or from outside
還是說從外地來的
We do see a different phenomenon
我們確實看到了不同的一個現象
For example, 5,000 years ago, 4,000 years ago, and 3,000 years ago
比方五千年的跟四千年的跟三千年前的
There is this difference between the north and the south
就有南北的這個差異
Even we now think that the place 5,000 years ago belonged to this Penghu
甚至於我們現在認為五千年前的這個有屬於這個澎湖的
Or it is likely to be where the ingredient on the other side is located.
或者是很可能會是對岸有的這個成分所在的
Because we have seen the so-called
因為我們看到了有所謂的這個立言的
Not in this place in Tainan
不是台南這個地方有的
For example, this burnt black
比方說這個燒黑的
Part of the burnt black part belongs to the local
燒黑的它有一部分是屬於local的
belonging to the local
屬於在地的
But it has some ingredients that belong to the Zhuoshui River
可是它有一些成分是屬於濁水溪
From a face on the other side of Zhuoshui River and Dadu River
濁水溪大渡溪那邊的一個顏相所出來的
So this is not a specialization
所以這個是不是一個專業化
we have now
我們現在有
I'm not doing it later
我不是後在做
so-called specialization
所謂的這種專業化
Or a phenomenon of the so-called logistics
或者是所謂的這種物流的一個現象
Well, we can't see this right now.
那這個目前我們沒有辦法來看
answer you very specifically
很具體的跟你回答
OK
好不好
Okay, thank you
好謝謝
Zhang Tianshi in the last two minutes
最後兩分鐘張天室
there is none left
沒有了
no more no more
沒有了沒有了
two minutes
還有兩分鐘來
last question
最後一個問題
because you have been there many times
因為你去很多次了
he has been there many times
他已經去很多次了
do a lot
做很多
you have been there many times
你去很多次了
Excuse me, I have doubts because I have been watching that
是請問一下 我有疑問就是一直在看那種
Is it because archaeological photos always dig squares?
就是考古一直的照片就是會挖方格嗎
I know squares are for positioning
我知道方格是用來定位的
Then you just dig over there to know where the stuff came from.
然後你就在那邊挖就可以知道東西是從哪個點挖出來
Then I have always had a doubt about the line in the middle of the grid.
那我一直有個疑惑就是方格中間的閣線
That is also a place to walk and a dividing point
那就是同時也是走路的地方嘛 也是劃分點
if there is
那如果有
Will there be any ruins? The relics are buried under that pavilion line.
會不會有什麼遺址啊 遺物就埋在那個閣線底下
how to find out
那要怎麼找出來
To avoid is to have loaded things being moved
避免就是有裝的東西被移動
Thanks
謝謝
I'm going to study next semester
下個學期來念書啦
Ha ha ha ha
哈哈哈哈
This to Cucumber or to that
這個到青瓜來或者是到那個
ok come on good question
好 來 很好的問題
come to this square
來 這個方格
If the results of our experiments are theoretically
如果從學理上面我們試驗的結果
2x2 2 meters by 2 meters
2x2 2公尺乘2公尺
This means that the two of you are working inside
這個是說你兩個人在裡面工作
3 to 4 is the most cost-effective one
3到4個是最成本經濟的一個
not just positioning
並不是只是定位
Positioning means that we have this square
定位是說我們在有這個方格
Everything comes out of this
所有的東西從這個裡面出來的
We put it away layer by layer
我們一層一層的收起來的
is to tell us the up and down of these things
就是告訴我們自己這些東西的上下
The positions of these relationships in space cannot be mixed up
空間的這些關係位置不可以混掉
But there is a line
可是有隔線的
you see the line
你看到有隔線的
That is what we call borrowing strength
那個是我們叫做借強
A method of excavating an early tradition
早期的傳統的一個發掘的一個方法
at the end you have something inside
到最後你裡面有東西
It's like a person's upper body is in
就好像一個人上半身在
The lower body in the carbon pit is in the middle of the divider
碳坑裡面下半身在那個隔線中間
then i will cut it off
那我就把它給切斷
grab it
抓起來
kill
打死
spank all the way to that
打屁股都打到那個
is not possible
是不可以
But now there are so-called
可是現在有所謂的
One of our excavations in Nanke
我們在南科的一個發掘
the whole compartment
整個隔
no middle no bit
沒有中間沒有位
But we jumped and dug. If there is a phenomenon in the middle, we have to dig a hole.
可是我們跳著挖 有現象在中間的我們要拓坑
In the end, there will be a flat phenomenon
拓到最後就會有一個平面的現象
different from mainland China
跟中國大陸就不一樣
When we talk to them in mainland China
中國大陸我們跟他們談的時候
He said your kind of digging children
他說你們那種挖小兒科
When we dig 10 meters, we call it 10 meters
我們一挖10公尺稱10公尺
They are called Dafang Carbon Fang
他們叫大方 碳方
yes
是
Then this is a different way of excavation
那這個就是不一樣的這種發掘的一個方式
it's different in america
在美國又不一樣
What we do in the United States is not changed at all
在美國我們在美國有做的根本就不化
You just take one of your phenomena
你就是以你的一個現象來取
But between layers
可是一層上下之間
between this direction
這個方位之間
this is still important
這個還是重要的
That means all of our unearthed stuff
就是說我們所有的出土的東西
They all have their ID cards
都是有它的身份證的
Otherwise, you can talk nonsense when the time comes
不然你到時候隨便亂說的
Mix up the top with the bottom
上層的跟下層的混掉
natural mix
自然的混
That is the one that got mixed up in the first place. If you mess with this side, then this is the most irrelevant thing. I can’t say that again.
那個是原本就混掉的,這個面,你去混,那這個就最不可涉,我不能再講那句話
I suggest that you have the opportunity to host one and ask him for advice in private, because at 9:00
我建議你們有機會主一個,私下跟他請教一下,因為9點
The main team went to visit, you see his 5,000-year-old man is sleeping next to 200-year-old
那個主個隊伍去參觀一下,你看他5000年的人睡在200年的旁邊
I feel that there is a lot of time. In Nanke and Tainan Science Park, there is no
感覺時間非常多,在南科,台南科學園區,還沒有
Not yet, thank you two for their wonderful speeches, thank you for participating
還沒有,謝謝他們兩位精彩的演講,謝謝各位參加